<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<root><title>30 Jalbak-Tash IV and VI</title><time>VIII-XI AD</time><hronology caption="Historical definition"></hronology><history></history><names caption="Names">Jalbak-Tash IV, Jalbak-Tash VI, Kalbak-Tash</names><place caption="Places">The Jalbak-Tash mountain is on right coast of river Chui near the confluence with river Katun. The rock with inscriptions is over the Chui highway on 721 km from Novosibirsk and 215 km from settlement Tashanta, on 13 km from village Jodro, on the border of Russia and Mongolia.  </place><store>The inscriptions is among the inscriptions marked Jalbak-Tash III to XIII on so called Jalbak-Tash I, Plane I, the top group.</store><general caption="Specification">Бітік жұқалап қашалған. Жақсы сақталған. Бірінші жолы 14 , екіншісі 3 жолдан тұрады.&#13;
Мәтінің таңбалары бас жағында биіктігі 2,3-2,4-тен 4,3-4,5 см (орташа 2,7-3 см), ені 1,4-1,6-дан 2 см болып кең қашалған, жарды бөліп түскен жарыққа жақындаған сайын жіңішкеріп кішірейіп кеткен (биіктігі 1,5-тен 2 см дейін). Таңбалардың арасы 0,5-тен 0,8 см дейін.&#13;
</general><description>The text is traced by thin solid lines. Stored well. The first text consists of 14 and the second of 3 signs. The texts starts by wide signs of size from 2.3-2.4 to 4.3-4.5 cm (average 2.7-3 cm) and ends up with signs of size from 1.4-1.6 to 2 cm. Signs become tight and small (height from 1.5 to 2 cm) to the crack on the rock. The gap between signs is from 0.5 to 0.8 cm.</description><size caption="Size">Length of the first line is 16 cm, the second is 4.5 cm; Height of signs is from 2.3 to 4.7 cm.</size><investigation caption="Researches">The inscriptions were noticed by Okladnikova in 1980. Nadeliyaev published for the first time in handwritten form. Kyzlasov assumes that two inscriptions marked separately IV and VI make up one two-lined vertical inscription  &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a name='source_517' class='myref' href='#label_517'&gt;517&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; (P.21-26). The lines were marked separately by Nadeliyaev and published as two independent inscriptions  &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a name='source_516' class='myref' href='#label_516'&gt;516&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; (P.77, 78). Cause of the separation was the gap of size 1.5 cm between the first five and the following signs. Two lines on top marked by number IV and one line on bottom is marked as VI.&#13;
Nadeliyaev’s translation: Ягыз-Эр! Думай про скарб, оружие, кочевье, скот, драгоценности и жильё! – Yagyz-Er! Think about goods and chattels, weapon, nomad’s camp, cattle, jewelry and dwelling.&#13;
Kyzlasov’s translation: О, бурая земля — о, та, которая должна называться священной моей землёю – O, brown earth – oh, that, which should be called my sacred land. &#13;
</investigation><details caption="Additional information"></details><pdfs caption="Full-text information"><pdf f_author="Кочеев В.А" f_title="Свод древнетюркских рунических памятников Горного Алтая. Горно-Алтайск: АКИН, 2006. – 52 с." f_in="" f_name="kocheev_altai.pdf"/><pdf f_author="Кызыласов И.Л" f_title="Новости тюркской рунологии. Выпуск 1. Енисейские надписи на горе Ялбак-таш (Горный Алтай). - М.: 2003, - 112 с." f_in="" f_name="kyzlasov_altai.pdf"/></pdfs><refs><ref nm="517">Наделяев В.М., 1981. Древнетюркские надписи Горного Алтая // Известия Сибирского отделения АН СССР, № 11, серия общественных наук, вып. 3. Новосибирск.</ref><ref nm="516">Бұл ескерткіш туралы деректер http://elbilge.ucoz.ru сайтында жарияланған Д.Д.Васильевтің еңбегі бойынша берілген. Қараңыз:  Васильев Д.Д. Корпус тюркских рунических памятников бассейна Енисея. – Л., 1983.</ref></refs></root>
