<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<root><title>Inscription on a stone implement found in Zhuban tobe</title><time>IX-X centuries</time><hronology caption="Historical definition"></hronology><history></history><names caption="Names">"The Zhuban Tobe inscription", "The Talas Runic inscriptions"</names><place caption="Places">The implement was found in small town Zhuban-tobe in 15 km west of Taraz city (former Zhambyl city).</place><store>The implement is stored in The Central State museum of Republic Kazakhstan. KP N20488.</store><general caption="Specification">Тас құралдың сынық тұсына қарсы  жиегiнде  1 жол мәтін қашалған. Таңба-әріп тереңдігі- 0,1 см.</general><description>One line of inscription is carved on edge opposite to the broken place of the stone implement. Depth of symbols is 0.1 cm. There are 6 signs (?) in line. </description><size caption="Size">Height of signs is 0.6 cm. Size: 11.7 х 5.2 х 4.8 sm</size><investigation caption="Researches">The implement was found by expedition under direction of K.M.Baypakov &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a name='source_472' class='myref' href='#label_472'&gt;472&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; in 1987. S.G.Klyashtornyi &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a name='source_473' class='myref' href='#label_473'&gt;473&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, A.S.Amanzholov &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a name='source_474' class='myref' href='#label_474'&gt;474&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; conducted researches of the inscription.</investigation><details caption="Additional information">Н.Базылхан "Көне түрік бітіктастары мен ескерткіштері (Орхон, Ениесей, Талас)" //"Қазақстан тарихы түркі тілді деректемелерде" атты сериясы бойынша. II том. - Алматы: Дайк-пресс, 2005. - Б.243.</details><pdfs caption="Full-text information"/><refs><ref nm="472">Аманжолов А.С.  Қола айнадағы қол таңба // Білім және еңбек, 1986, №2, 26-27 б. ; Аманжолов А.С.  Батыс Қазақстаннан табылған қола айнадағы көне жазу //  Түркі филологиясы және жазу тарихы , Алматы, 1996, 90-92б.;  Руническая надпись на бронзовом зеркале (Западный Казахстан)   // История и теория древнетюркского письма. Алматы, 2003. С. 247-248.</ref><ref nm="473">Байпаков К.М.  Средневековые города Казахстана на великом Шелковом пути . Алматы, 1998, С. 91.  (Камень с древнетюркской рунической надписью «Атлах» . VI-VIII вв.)</ref><ref nm="474">Кляшторный С.Г. Рунические памятники Таласа (проблемы датировки и топографии) // Из истории и археологии древнего Тянь-Шаня.  Бишкек, 1995, С. 154-159.</ref></refs></root>
