<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<root><title>Qozy-Korpesh and Bayan sulu tomb, The</title><time></time><hronology caption="Historical definition"></hronology><history></history><names caption="Names"></names><place caption="Places">The tomb is located on high hill on right coast of Ayagoz river near Tansyk village. N 47017´38.5´´ - Е 79042´12.7´´.</place><store></store><general caption="Specification">The Kozy-Korpesh and Bayan sulu tomb is made in a quadrangle form. Entrance of a monument is in east side. There are two sarcophaguses inside of the monument. These structures are added at restoration. A monument is made from natural stones. There is a small window on southern wall on three meters high from ground. It was made during the restoration. There was no window in the beginning.</general><description>The basis is lifted directly up to 1 meter and then narrowed.  There are two domes over the tomb, one inside another. </description><size caption="Size">The sizes of the bottom basis are 7.60 х 7.50 m. Height is about 11 m. The top of the internal dome is 6 m in height. Height of the door is 2,15 m and width is 87 cm. Thickness of walls near the entrance is 2.10 m. Sizes of the bottom basis of internal walls are 3.20 х 3.20 m.</size><investigation caption="Researches">A.Divaev, P.Semyonov-Tyanshanskyi, W.Radloff, S.Valikhanov  &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a name='source_486' class='myref' href='#label_486'&gt;486&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; conducted researches. Expeditions of Academy of Sciences of Kazakh SSR under direction N.A.Abramov in 1858, N.N.Pantusov in 1898, A.Margulan &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a name='source_487' class='myref' href='#label_487'&gt;487&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; in 1952 conducted special research works.</investigation><details caption="Additional information">There is an Old Turkic writing under the window. N.Bazylhan claims that G.Aydarov could leave this inscription in middle of XX century. The same inscription is found on "Budda rocks" on the coast of Ile river in 120 km from Almaty city, Kazakstan (See pictures). </details><pdfs caption="Full-text information"/><refs><ref nm="486">Кубарев Г.В., Цэвээндорж Д. Древности Алтая –известия лаборатории археологии №4. Горно-алтайск, ГАГУ, 1999. С. 169-172. ; Kubarev V.D. and Tseveendorj D. Ancient Turkic memorials in the Altai / Archaelogy, Ethnology &amp; Anthropology of Eurasia  1(9) 2002. pp. </ref><ref nm="487">Валиханов Ч.Ч. Собрание сочинений в пяти томах, том 1, А.-А., 1984, с.309, 310.</ref></refs></root>
