<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<root><title>Old Turkic writing on a bronze mirror found in Irtysh</title><time>IX-X centuries</time><hronology caption="Historical definition"></hronology><history></history><names caption="Names">"Runic writing on Irtysh bronze mirror", "The Irtysh Runic Samples"</names><place caption="Places">The mirror was found in an old Turkic barrow ("the 146th barrow") near the village "Zevakino Shemonaihinsk" on coast of Irtysh river of East Kazakhstan oblast. Remains of a woman and some subjects were found in the barrow.</place><store>The mirror is stored in the local history museum of East Kazakhstan oblast (?).</store><general caption="Specification">Қола айнаның  жиегi мен iшкі шеңберінде  дөңгелене үшкiр темiр затпен қашалып 2 жол мәтін жазылған.</general><description>2 lines of the writing are carved round by sharp iron subject on edge and on an internal circle of the bronze mirror. There are 20 signs in the first line and 11 signs in the second line. </description><size caption="Size">Height of symbols is 1.2-1.5 cm. The length of circle of the mirror is 10 cm. The thickness of the mirror is 1 cm.</size><investigation caption="Researches">F.H.Arslanova found in 1969. F.H.Arslanova, S.G.Kljashtornyi  &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a name='source_468' class='myref' href='#label_468'&gt;468&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, A.S.Amanzholov  &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a name='source_399' class='myref' href='#label_399'&gt;399&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; conducted researches of the writing.</investigation><details caption="Additional information">Н.Базылхан "Көне түрік бітіктастары мен ескерткіштері (Орхон, Ениесей, Талас)" //"Қазақстан тарихы түркі тілді деректемелерде" атты сериясы бойынша. II том. - Алматы: Дайк-пресс, 2005. - Б.241.</details><pdfs caption="Full-text information"/><refs><ref nm="468">Amanjolov A.S.  Kazakistan’da bulunan Cin aynasi ile sasanid tabagindaki runik turk yazilari // Turk Dili Arastirmalari, Bulleten, 1993, Ankara, s. 115-119. ; Аманжолов А.С. Руническая надпись на китайском (Восточный Казахстан)   // История и теория древнетюркского письма. Алматы, 2003. С. 199-200. ; А. С. Аманжолов Түркі филологиясы және жазу тарихы , Алматы, 1996, 95 б.</ref><ref nm="399">Аманжолов А.С.Руническая надпись на бронзовом зеркале местного производства (Восточный Казахстан) // История и теория древнетюркского письма. Алматы, 2003. С.201-202. ; А.С.Аманжолов Түркі филологиясы және жазу тарихы, Алматы, 1996, 95 б. &#13;
	Қола айнадағы мәтін жайында А.С.Аманжоловтың транскрипциясы мен орысша, қазақша аудармасы:		1. jebči jegren ar lü – Покровитель –красновато рыжий дракон&#13;
	 2. iši künisin esser qutï basar – Если знатная женщина уменьшает (сдерживает) свою зваисть, она обретает счастье. &#13;
 1. Жебеушi қызыл күрең айдаһар &#13;
 2. Әйел күншілдігін азайтса құты қонады.</ref></refs></root>
