<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<root><title>Baibalyq fortress, The</title><time></time><hronology caption="Historical definition"></hronology><history></history><names caption="Names"></names><place caption="Places">The Baibalyq fortress is located on coast of Selenga river, in 11 km west of Khutag Ondor sum of Bulgan aimag at N49º23´38´´ - E102º30´21´´, 1127 m above the sea level.</place><store>Солтүстік ендік – 49 023 ' 38 '', шығыс бойлық – 102030 ' 21''. Теңіз деңгейінен:  1127 м. Бұлғын аймағы, Хутаг-Өндөр  сұмынынан 11 км батыста. Селеңгі  өзен бойында орналасқан. </store><general caption="Specification">The Baibalyq fortress (the local population called Byibulag) constructed by Sogdian and Chinese people under order of Eletmish, the kagan (rules in 747-759) of Uighur kagandom.</general><description>Ұйғыр қағандығының Ел-етміш Білге қаған тарапынан соғдылықтар мен қытайлықтарға салдырған Бай-балық  қаласы  ( жергiлiктi халық : Бийбулаг  деп атайды)   </description><size caption="Size">1st construction: 238х235х378х232 m, 2nd construction: 142х149х158х149 m, 3rd construction: 329х314х332х320 m</size><investigation caption="Researches">S.V.Kiselyov, H.Perlee conducted excavations in 1949. Descriptions of this fortress published S.G.Klyashtornyi in 1975  &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a name='source_462' class='myref' href='#label_462'&gt;462&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, J.S.Hudjakov published in 1982 and 1986  &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a name='source_463' class='myref' href='#label_463'&gt;463&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Mongolian and Japanese scientists D.Bayar, N.Shirayshi, T.Battulga  &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a name='source_464' class='myref' href='#label_464'&gt;464&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; conducted special researches in the fortress in 1996-1998. They made topographical portrayals, measurements of three constructions, collected and elevated archeological relics. They made drawings of 4 lion statues and collected general information on the fortress place and its structure. Basing on these researches, well-known Mongolian archeologist D.Bayar has published a scientific article about the Baibalyq fortress  &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a name='source_465' class='myref' href='#label_465'&gt;465&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.</investigation><details caption="Additional information"></details><pdfs caption="Full-text information"/><refs><ref nm="462">Осы бітіктас, ескерткіштерінңі мәтіндік, тiлдiк зерттеулерiн  В.В. Радлов,  П.М. Мелиоранский, Ю.Немет , С.Е. Малов, Х.Н. Орхун, И.А. Батманов, А.С. Аманжолов, Ч. Жумагулов, С.Г.Кляшторный, А.С. Аманжолов  т.б. ғалымдар жүргiздi.   &#13;
1961, 1963, 1977-ншi жылдары 6, 7, 8, 9, 10-ншi ескерткiштер, жартастағы ұсақ жазулар табылды (П.Н.Кожемяко, Д.Ф.Винник, Ч.Жумагулов, У.Асаналиев, К.Аширалиев, Г.Карагулова). &#13;
1998-2000 жылдары сегiз жазу табылды (К.Табалдиев, О.Солтобаев).&#13;
</ref><ref nm="463">Кляшторный С.Г. Древние города Монголии. Древние города. Материалы к Всесоюзной конференции «Культура Средней Азии и Казахстана в эпоху раннего средневековья» (Пенджикент,октябрь 1977г. ). Л., 1977. С.65.</ref><ref nm="464">Худяков  Ю.С. Памятники уйгурской культуры в Монголии.  Центральная Азия и соседние территорий в средние века. Новосибирск, 1990. С. 84-89. </ref><ref nm="465">Provisional report of researches on historical sites and inscriptions in Mongolia from 1996 to 1998 . Edited by Takao Moriyasu  and Ayudai Ochir.  The Society of Central Eurasian Studies, Toyonaka, Osaka University,  1999. Бийбулагийн балгасыг судласан хээрийн шинжилгээний хэсгийн тайлан. Д.Баяр, Н.Ширайши, Ц.Баттулга  ТХГБС. УБ., 1998. </ref></refs></root>
