<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<root><title>“Qara Qatu” (Ereen Kharganat) inscription, The </title><time></time><hronology caption="Historical definition"></hronology><history>The inscription probably belongs to II-III centuries.</history><names caption="Names">“Qara Qatu”, “Ereen Kharganat”</names><place caption="Places">The inscription is written on right side of “It urgen” mountain. The mountain is located in 15 km from the Ölgii city, the capital of Bayan-Ölgii aimag of Mongolia, near east coast of  “Kara Katu” river in 9 km southeast of Bugyt sum. </place><store>The inscription is its site.</store><general caption="Specification">There are three big and seven small stone barrows on northern and east sides of the mountain. The barrows fallen into decay by time. There are two small statues among them. There are carved figures of roe, wild ram, deer and other animals on a sheep statue.</general><description>There is one clear sign on east side of the inscription. Other small lines and hyphens are indistinct as a result of modern intruders.</description><size caption="Size">The height of the stone screen with old Turkic inscription is 2 m 89 cm, width 35-37 cm.</size><investigation caption="Researches">The first report of  “Ereen Kharganat” inscription was published by archeologist D.Erdenebaatar  &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a name='source_433' class='myref' href='#label_433'&gt;433&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. The young scientist, historian T.Battulga  &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a name='source_434' class='myref' href='#label_434'&gt;434&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; gave explanation using that report. N.Bazylhan  &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a name='source_431' class='myref' href='#label_431'&gt;431&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and other scientists conducted researches later.</investigation><details caption="Additional information"></details><pdfs caption="Full-text information"/><refs><ref nm="433">Эрдэнэбаатар Д. 1990 онд Баян-Өлгей аймагт ажилласан хээрийн шинжилгээний тайлан. ТХГБСХ. Улаанбаатар, 1990; Эрдэнэбаатар Д. Монгол нутгаас олдсон эртний бичээсұұд. "Ил товчоо" сонин. 1991.</ref><ref nm="434">Баттулга Ц. Эрээн Харганатын тұрэг бичээс. Археологийн судлал. Боть.15, дэвтэр 3, Улаанбаатар.1995. 65-69 х.</ref><ref nm="431">Базылхан Б. Эртний Тұрэг бичээсний хэлний ұгийн бұтэц. Улаанбаатар. 1984. 98 х; Cэвортян С.Э. Этимологический словарь тюркских языков М., 1980. С.104-106. Древнетюркский словарь Л., 1969.С. 327-328;</ref></refs></root>
