<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<root><title>Doloodoyn stele and inscription, The</title><time>VIII-IX centuries</time><hronology caption="Historical definition">VIII-IX ғасыр.</hronology><history>The inscription belongs to Kirghiz state epoch. The text of the inscription is very similar to Yenissey inscriptions.</history><names caption="Names">“ The Doloodoyn monument”</names><place caption="Places">The stele was found in Har Us district of Turgen sum of Uvs aimag of Mongolia.</place><store>The stele is moved to the local history museum of Ulaangom sum of Uvs aimag.</store><general caption="Specification">The stele was in a big barrow (a circle – 17.5 m). The stele is made from granite of red-brown color. </general><description>The inscription consists of 4 lines. The lines consist of 68 symbols and similar to Yenissey writings. But about 30 of symbols are invisible.</description><size caption="Size">Height of symbols is 7.5-8 cm, width is 6.9-7.1 cm, depth is 0.1-0.2 cm. Length of the first line (D-1) approximately is 105 cm, the second line length (D-2) is 102 cm, the third line (D-3) length is 103 cm, the fourth line (D-4) length is 102 cm.</size><investigation caption="Researches">Mongolian archeologist T.Dorzhsuren &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a name='source_251' class='myref' href='#label_251'&gt;251&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; found in 1955. No solid research of the inscription was conducted yet.</investigation><details caption="Additional information">Н.Базылхан "Көне түрік бітіктастары мен ескерткіштері (Орхон, Ениесей, Талас)" //"Қазақстан тарихы түркі тілді деректемелерде" атты сериясы бойынша. II том. - Алматы: Дайк-пресс, 2005. - Б.160-161.</details><pdfs caption="Full-text information"><pdf f_author="Баттулга Ц" f_title="Монголын руни бичгийн бага дурсгалууд. Улаанбаатар. - 2005 (1)" f_in="" f_name="mongol1.pdf"/><pdf f_author="Баттулга Ц" f_title="Монголын руни бичгийн бага дурсгалууд. Улаанбаатар. - 2005 (2)" f_in="" f_name="mongol2.pdf"/><pdf f_author="Баттулга Ц" f_title="Монголын руни бичгийн бага дурсгалууд. Улаанбаатар. - 2005 (3)" f_in="" f_name="mongol3.pdf"/></pdfs><refs><ref nm="251">Доржсүрэн Ц.Долоодойн булш ба түүний бичээс // Археологийн судлал. Studio Archaeologica. Tomus I, Fasc 2, Улаанбаатар, 1960, х. 3-4.&#13;
	Сонымен қатар аталмыш бітіктас жайында мына еңбектерде мәліметтер жарияланған: Rіtchen B. Les dessigns pictographiques et les inscriptions sur les rochers et sur les steles en Mongolie. Corpus Scriptorum Mongolorum Instituti Linguae et Litterarum Academiae Scientiarum Reipublicae Populi Mongolici, Tom. 16, Fasc. 1, Улаанбаатар. 1968, 41 т.; Болд Л.БНМАУ-ын нутаг дахь хадны бичээс (Түрэг бичгийн дурсгал). Улаанбаатар, 1990, 30 т.; Монгол нутаг дахь түүх соелын дурсгал. Улаанбаатар. 1999. 209-210-р тал.</ref></refs></root>
