<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<root><title>Old Turkic writing on a copper coin</title><time>VI-VIII centuries</time><hronology caption="Historical definition">VI-VIII ғасыр.</hronology><history></history><names caption="Names">“Writings on a coin”, “A coin with Turkic writings”</names><place caption="Places">The coin was found by archeological expedition in Dornod aimag of Mongolia.</place><store>It is stored in laboratory of Archeology Institute of Mongolia (?)  &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a name='source_242' class='myref' href='#label_242'&gt;242&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.</store><general caption="Specification"></general><description>There are two Chinese hieroglyphs on obverse of the coin. And there is old Turkic writing of 21 symbols on reverse. It was written with a sharp needle with depth of 4-5 mm.</description><size caption="Size">Coin sizes: circle length is 2.5 cm, quadrangular hole size is 1х1 cm, thickness is 0.1 cm.</size><investigation caption="Researches">The coin was found by Mongolian archeologist N.Ser-Odzhav &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a name='source_243' class='myref' href='#label_243'&gt;243&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; in 1961. G.Klyashtornyi &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a name='source_244' class='myref' href='#label_244'&gt;244&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, S.Harzhaubay &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a name='source_245' class='myref' href='#label_245'&gt;245&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; examined the old Turkic writing.</investigation><details caption="Additional information">Н.Базылхан "Көне түрік бітіктастары мен ескерткіштері (Орхон, Ениесей, Талас)" //"Қазақстан тарихы түркі тілді деректемелерде" атты сериясы бойынша. II том. - Алматы: Дайк-пресс, 2005. - Б.157.</details><pdfs caption="Full-text information"/><refs><ref nm="242">Қазір аталмыш мыс тиынның қайда екені де белгісіз. Оны Моңғолия Археология институтының лабораториялық сақтау қоймасынан таба алмадық. Бұл туралы анық-қанығын білетін де ешкім болмай шықты.</ref><ref nm="243">Сэр-Оджав Н.Эртний түрэгүүд (VI-V1II ууун) //Studiа Archaeologica Instituti Historiae Academiae Scientiarum Reipublicae Populi Mongolici, Том. 5, Fasc. 2., Улаанбаатар, 1970, Зураг-21.; Сэр-Оджав Н.Монголын эртний түүх. Улаанбаатар, 1977, (Дорнодоос олдсон зоосны бичээс) 141- т.</ref><ref nm="244">Кляшторный С.Г.Монета с рунической надписью из Монголии // Тюркологическая сборник-1972. Москва, 1973, C. 334-338.</ref><ref nm="245">«...гунны употребляя в обращений также монеты Ханьского периода «У-ши», на одной стороне монеты оставили свою письменность, что вновь подтверждает гипотезу некоторых ученых, считающих, что Гунны использовали тюркскую письменность» дейді С.Харжаубай. // Қараңыз: Харжаубай С.Эртний гурван бичээс (Тэвшийн бичээс) // Археологийн судлал. Studio Archaeologica Instituti Historiae Academiae Scientiarum Reipublicae Populi Mongolic. Tomus VII, Fasc 10-18, Улаанбаатар, 1979, х. 32-35.</ref></refs></root>
