<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<root><title>Inscription Ordu-balyq I (Karabalghasun I) </title><time>Approximately in 808-832 AD</time><hronology caption="Historical definition">шамамен 808-832 жж</hronology><history>The stele was made in honor of Bilge Tengri Uighur kagan.</history><names caption="Names">“ The Khara Balgasun monument”, “The 1st monument of Ordu balyq”</names><place caption="Places">The stele was found in south of Ordu-balyq city (local people call it Kharbalgas i.e. “The Black town” in Hotont sum of Arkhangai aimag at N47º23´ - E102º28´. </place><store>There was a capital of ancient Turkic and Uighur kagandoms at the place. The stele is broken in many fragments. Many of them are on the site.&#13;
The fragment with dragon image is kept in cultural center of Hoton sum. Two fragments with Sogdian and Chinese inscriptions are kept in St.-Petersburg. The location of other fragments except written above is unknown.&#13;
</store><general caption="Specification">There are four fragments with old Turkic inscriptions. One of the fragments is top part of the stele. It is rounded and has image of a dragon. There are also three fragments with Sogdian and Chinese inscriptions and 2 stones like pedestal.</general><description>The stele with is made of light grey marble. There were read thirty words out of nine fragments with different sizes.</description><size caption="Size"></size><investigation caption="Researches">N.M.Yadrintsev conducted researches in 1889 &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a name='source_120' class='myref' href='#label_120'&gt;120&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. W.Radloff made the first translation of old Turkic inscriptions and published pictures and paper copy &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a name='source_226' class='myref' href='#label_226'&gt;226&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. V.P.Vasilev made translation of Chinese inscription in 1897. The Mongolian-Japanese joint expedition conducted research of the stele in 1996-1997 &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a name='source_230' class='myref' href='#label_230'&gt;230&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Kazakh scientists conducted researches in 2001 and 2004. </investigation><details caption="Additional information">Н.Базылхан "Көне түрік бітіктастары мен ескерткіштері (Орхон, Ениесей, Талас)" //"Қазақстан тарихы түркі тілді деректемелерде" атты сериясы бойынша. II том. - Алматы: Дайк-пресс, 2005. - Б.149-151.</details><pdfs caption="Full-text information"><pdf f_author="Баттулга Ц" f_title="Монголын руни бичгийн бага дурсгалууд. Улаанбаатар. - 2005 (1)" f_in="" f_name="mongol1.pdf"/><pdf f_author="Баттулга Ц" f_title="Монголын руни бичгийн бага дурсгалууд. Улаанбаатар. - 2005 (2)" f_in="" f_name="mongol2.pdf"/><pdf f_author="Баттулга Ц" f_title="Монголын руни бичгийн бага дурсгалууд. Улаанбаатар. - 2005 (3)" f_in="" f_name="mongol3.pdf"/></pdfs><refs><ref nm="120">Ядринцев Н.М.Отчет экспедиции на Орхон, совершенной в 1889 г., по поручению Восточно-Сибирского отдела императорского Географического общества. Труды Орхонской экспедиции. Вып.1, 1892. С.51-113.</ref><ref nm="226">Radloff W. Das Uigurusche Denkmal von Kara-Balgasun // Die Alttürkischen Inscrihpiften de Mongolei. Dritte Lieferung Die Denkmäler von Koscho-Zaidam, die ubrigen denkmaler des Orchon bechens und denkmaler im flussgebiete des Jenissei. St.Petersburg, 1895. p. 283-298. ; Радлов В.В.Предварительный отчет о результатах экспедиции для археологического исследования бассейна р. Орхона // Сборник трудов Орхонской экспедиции, I, Санкт-Петербург, 1892, С.1-54. ; Radloff W. Atlas der Alterthümer der Mongolei. Arbeiten der Orchon Expedition. I-IV. St.Petersburg, 1892, 1893, 1896, 1899. ; Радлов В.В.Атлас древностей Монголии. Труды Орхонской экспедиции, I-IV. СПб., 1892, 1893, 1896, 1899.</ref><ref nm="230">Takao Moriyasu, Yutaka Yoshida, Akio Katayama (Qara-Balgasun Inscription) // Provisional report of researches on historical sites and inscriptions in Mongolia from 1996 to 1998 . Edited by Takao Moriyasu and Ayudai Ochir. The Society of Central Eurasian Studies, Toyonaka, Osaka University, 1999. pp. 209-224.</ref></refs></root>
