<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<root><title>“Ongot” Memorial Complex, The</title><time>V-VII  ғасыр</time><hronology caption="Historical definition"></hronology><history>One of the most ancient traditional complexes devoted to a Turkic kagan.</history><names caption="Names">“The Ongot monument”, “Ongotyin Khoshoot”</names><place caption="Places">The complex is located on northwest coast of the Tuul river in 88 km west of city Ulaanbaatar in Altanbulag sum of Töv aimag in Mongolia at N47º33´102´´ - E105º51´002´´, 1146 m above the sea level. </place><store>The memorial complex is on its site. But locations of some fragments are unknown.</store><general caption="Specification">The complex has the largest number of stone sculptures and balbals (line of erected stones) among other memorial complexes of the Turkic epoch. The complex includes a stone box, stone sculptures (34 units), a lion statue, a ram statue, balbal stones (525 pieces).</general><description></description><size caption="Size"></size><investigation caption="Researches">N.M.Yadrintsev &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a name='source_475' class='myref' href='#label_475'&gt;475&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; conducted research of the complex  in 1891. D.A.Klements conducted research in 1893. G.I.Borovka conducted excavations in 1925 for the first time. Then the Soviet-Mongolian historical and cultural expedition conducted archeological excavations. During those excavations there were found fragments of ceramic dishes and some hundreds of “sirge” iron weapon often used by nomads on war. There were found 13 bases of wooden columns proving existence of some wooden structures. V.E.Voitov  &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a name='source_476' class='myref' href='#label_476'&gt;476&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, D.Bayar  &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a name='source_477' class='myref' href='#label_477'&gt;477&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; gave some scientific descriptions of the complex in 1987. V.E.Voitov claimed that the complex had been built in honor of Inan kagan in 645-646 year  &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a name='source_478' class='myref' href='#label_478'&gt;478&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.</investigation><details caption="Additional information"></details><pdfs caption="Full-text information"/><refs><ref nm="475">Аманжолов А.С.  Две таласские рунические надписи из городища Атлах   //  Тюркская руническая графика – II  (наглядный материал).  Алма-Ата., 1981, с. 12. ; А.С. Аманжолов Атлақ мекен орнынан табылған екі руникалық талас жазуы (Жамбыл облысы , Байзақ ауданы) //  Түркі филологиясы және жазу тарихы , Алматы, 1996, 47 б. .;  Аманжолов А.С.   Две таласские рунические надписи из городища Атлах //История и теория древнетюркского письма. Алматы, 2003. С. 96.</ref><ref nm="476">Ядринцев Н.М. Отчет и дневник с путешествия  по Орхону и в южный Хангай в 1891 г. // Труды Орхонской экспедиции.  Т. Y, 1892. С.51-113.</ref><ref nm="477">Войтов В.Е., Баяр Д. Новые археологические открытия в Хангае // Информационный бюллетень. Международная ассоциация по изучению культур Центральной Азии. М., 1989. Вып. 16 ;  Войтов В.Е. Древнетюркский пантеон и модель мироздания в культово-поминальных памятниках Монголии VI-VIII в. М., 1996. С. 39. </ref><ref nm="478">Баяр Д. Туулын хөндий дэх Түрэгийн өмнөх үеийн хүн чулууны тухай. SA. T.VII, f.10. Улаанбаатар, 1979. 3-22 –р тал. ; Баяр Д. Монголын төв нутаг дахь Түрэгийн хүн чулуу. Улаанбаатар. 1997. 83-85-р тал..       </ref></refs></root>
