<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<root><title>“Olon Nuur” Memorial Complex, The</title><time></time><hronology caption="Historical definition"></hronology><history></history><names caption="Names">“Olon Nuur memorial inscriptions”, “Олон Нуурын Хөндийн дурсгал”</names><place caption="Places">Olon Nuur is located at 46°35΄03.0˝, 100°04΄43.9˝, 2048 m, to the south of the Khangai mountain range, the district of Galuut, in Bayanhongor county. </place><store>Two statues were moved to Bayanhongor local historical museum. Other parts are still on the site.</store><general caption="Specification">The complex consists of 1 stone box (4 walls), statues, stone supports, line of 54 balbals lasts up to 784 m.</general><description>There are two vertical and one horizontal line of inscription on edge of a wall. The horizontal line is damaged.&#13;
And there is a line on a broken part of another wall. Unfortunately it is possible to read only 3 signs of the text.</description><size caption="Size">1) Sizes of the wall with inscription: length 221 cm, height 108 cm, width 16 cm. Height of signs 4-6.7 cm, width is between 2.3-5.1 cm . &#13;
2) Sizes of the broken part with inscription: length 93 cm, height 76 cm, width 11 cm. Height of signs 14.1-7.5 cm, width is between 4.5-6.9 cm.</size><investigation caption="Researches">2005 жылдың қыркүйегінде осы кешеннің тоналғаны туралы ақпарат түседі. 2008 жылдың маусымында Моңғолия Ғылым Академиясы проф.Д.Баяр бастаған, құрамында Р.Мөнхтулга, С.Хүрэлсүх бар экспедицияны кешенді іздеуге жібереді. Экспедиция кешенді тауып, 13-16 маусымда қазба жұмыстарын жүргізеді. Аталмыш ғалымдар осы ескерткіштің фотосуреттерін, сызбаларын, транскрипциясын, оқылуын, түсініктемелерін және моңғол, ағылшын тіліне аудармасын алғаш рет жария етті. &#13;
«Мәдени мұра» бағдарламасы аясында Қазақстан Республикасының Мәдениет және ақпарат министрлігінің қолдауымен  Қазақстан Республикасы Президенттік мәдениет орталығы 2008 жылдың 12 желтоқсанында «Қазақстан: өткені, бүгінгісі және болашағы» (Батыс Түрк қағандығы) атты Халықаралық ғылыми-тәжірибелік конференцияда Проф.Д.Баяр кешен туралы ғылыми көпшілік алдында баяндады.</investigation><details caption="Additional information"></details><pdfs caption="Full-text information"><pdf f_author="Баяр Д., Мөнхтулга Р., Хүрэлсүх С" f_title="Олон Нуурын Хөндийн дурсгал = A report on the newly found memorial inscriptions from &amp;quot;Olon Nuur&amp;quot; valley" f_in="" f_name="Bayar0.pdf"/><pdf f_author="Баяр Д., Мөнхтулга Р., Хүрэлсүх С" f_title="Олон Нуурын Хөндийн дурсгал = A report on the newly found memorial inscriptions from &amp;quot;Olon Nuur&amp;quot; valley (photos)" f_in="" f_name="Bayar1.pdf"/><pdf f_author="Баяр Д., Мөнхтулга Р., Хүрэлсүх С" f_title="Олон Нуурын Хөндийн дурсгал = A report on the newly found memorial inscriptions from &amp;quot;Olon Nuur&amp;quot; valley (photos)" f_in="" f_name="Bayar2.pdf"/><pdf f_author="Баяр Д., Мөнхтулга Р., Хүрэлсүх С" f_title="Олон Нуурын Хөндийн дурсгал = A report on the newly found memorial inscriptions from &amp;quot;Olon Nuur&amp;quot; valley (copies)" f_in="" f_name="Bayar3.pdf"/><pdf f_author="Баяр Д., Мөнхтулга Р., Хүрэлсүх С" f_title="Олон Нуурын Хөндийн дурсгал = A report on the newly found memorial inscriptions from &amp;quot;Olon Nuur&amp;quot; valley (copies)" f_in="" f_name="Bayar4.pdf"/></pdfs><refs/></root>
