<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<root><title>Dayan Memorial Complex, The</title><time>VI-VIII  ғғ</time><hronology caption="Historical definition"></hronology><history>The complex belongs to the western Turkic ethnos.</history><names caption="Names">The local people call the complex “The Dayan Bataar monuments”, “The Dayan lake monuments”.</names><place caption="Places">The memorial complex is located on southeast side of lake Dayan Nuur of Tsengel sum in Bayan-Ölgii aimag at N48º16´063´´ - E088º52´982´´, on 2241m above the sea level. </place><store>The memorial is on its site.</store><general caption="Specification">There are two quadrangle barrows, a stone sculpture and a stele.</general><description></description><size caption="Size">The barrows’ size: 4х4 m.&#13;
The stone sculpture size: 160х35-39х18-19 cm.&#13;
</size><investigation caption="Researches">G.N.Potanin &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a name='source_482' class='myref' href='#label_482'&gt;482&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; for the first time has published portrayals of the stone sculpture. The Mongolian archeologist N.Ser-Odzhav  &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a name='source_483' class='myref' href='#label_483'&gt;483&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; has published a brief announcement in 1960. He considers a cross sign on the chest of the sculpture as Jesus Christ symbol. &#13;
But D.Bayar claims that the sign is not Jesus Christ cross, but sign of an eagle  &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a name='source_484' class='myref' href='#label_484'&gt;484&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&#13;
D.Kubarev and D.Tseveendorzh, members of Mongolia-USA-Russia joint expedition, have published a general description and some pictures of the “Dayan” memorial complex   &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a name='source_485' class='myref' href='#label_485'&gt;485&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&#13;
</investigation><details caption="Additional information"></details><pdfs caption="Full-text information"/><refs><ref nm="482">Баяр Д. Монголын төв нутаг дахь Түрэгийн хүн чулуу. Улаанбаатар. 1997. 85-86-р тал..       </ref><ref nm="483">Потанин  Г.Н. очерки северо-западной Монголии. Вып. 2., СПб., 1881. с. 72. </ref><ref nm="484">Сэр-оджав Н. Баян-Өлгйи аймгийн археологийн дурсгалыг судалсан нь. Түүхийн судлал. Улаанбаатар, 1963. 17-26. </ref><ref nm="485">Баяр Д., Эрдэнбаатар Д. Монгол алтайн хүн чулуун хөшөө. Улаанбатар, 1999. ; Баяр Д. Даян баатарын хөшөө . /  Монгол нутаг дахь түүх соелын дурсгал (сэдэвчилсэн лавлах). Улаанбаатар, 1999. 102.</ref></refs></root>
