<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<root><title>Tatpar (Kutlug) kagan memorial complex, The</title><time>581-582</time><hronology caption="Historical definition">581-582 ж.</hronology><history>In turk.: Kutlug; in Chinese sources: Ta-po //Tobo; in sogdian.: Maga Tatpar kagan  &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a name='source_74' class='myref' href='#label_74'&gt;74&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Ancestor of Tatpar kagan was Bumin kagan from “ačïna” generation (the official title is “El kagan”; ruled in 552-599). Bumin kagan's son Kara (“Aju”) the kagan ruled Turkic people after Bumin kagan. Then the younger brother of Kara kagan Mukan (“Turk Kulik El”) kagan ruled. Tatpar (Makan tegi) is younger brother of Mukan. Tatpar kagan sat on the throne in 571-582. During this period Turk people turned to a great empire on the “Silk way”. &#13;
It is known from Chinese sources, that Tatpar kagan supported the Buddhism.&#13;
</history><names caption="Names">“Bugatin dursgal”  &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a name='source_75' class='myref' href='#label_75'&gt;75&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; (in mong.: statue of deer), “The Bugut inscription”, “the Complex of sacred places of Bugiti”, “the Complex of Tatpar kagan monuments”, “the memorial complex of Tatpar kagan”</names><place caption="Places">Found in 10 km west from Bugit (Ih tamir) sum in Arkhangai aimag of Mongolia, at N47º 49´, E101º 16´.</place><store>A barrow, some rests of walls, stone balbals (the erected stone sequence), etc. are on the site. A stele and a stone turtle are put on the central square of Tsetserleg city’s local history museum (Arkhangai aimag). A fragment of the top part is kept in the museum warehouse.</store><general caption="Specification">The stone fences (bariq) in form of walls (40-50m), aryks (ditches) (width - 4-5 m, depth - 2m), the tent-dome with wooden racks, a stele, stone clusters (7.5х7.5m), balbals  (528-276 stones last up to 300m) devoted to a kagan. The stele erected on the stone turtle support. The stone balbals are above 276.</general><description>The stele was put under a ceil with eight columns &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a name='source_76' class='myref' href='#label_76'&gt;76&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&#13;
There is an inscription of sogdian letters in old sogdian language on face (В-2, 19 lines) and on each side (on right side: В-1, 5 lines; on left side: В-3, 5 lines) of yellowish clay stele. Depth of letters is 0.1-0.3 mm. And there is an inscription of brahmi-old Sanskrit (language is unknown) on back side.</description><size caption="Size">Height of the stele is 198 cm, width is 70 cm, and thickness is 20 cm. Sizes of the stone turtle: 92.5 х 58.5 х 63 cm.</size><investigation caption="Researches">The complex was found by Mongolian archeologist T.Dorzhsuren in 1956. He wrote: «Diameter of the circular stone cluster was 8 m. The half of a stele was seen up on front of it. The half of this seen part of the stele was damaged. The rest was like the wolf’s image with open mouth and omitted head. There were old Uigur writings on front face and each side of the stele. And there was unknown inscription on back side. We were very excited by the found unknown inscription. This could be a small inscription of the state Kidan. But the final conclusion should be made after detailed studying of the inscription» &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a name='source_77' class='myref' href='#label_77'&gt;77&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. &#13;
Well-known Mongolian archeologist N.Ser-Odzhav claims that the inscription is “the Uighur writing” in his scientific article named “Archeologic inscriptions of Mongolia” published in 1960  &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a name='source_78' class='myref' href='#label_78'&gt;78&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Academician B.Rintchen included it to the atlas of «Corpus Scriptorum Mongolorum»  &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a name='source_79' class='myref' href='#label_79'&gt;79&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; in 1968. V.A.Livshits, S.G.Klyashtornyi defined, that the inscription was old Sogdian language &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a name='source_80' class='myref' href='#label_80'&gt;80&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; in 1969. The members of Mongol-Soviet expedition V.E.Voitov, S.G.Klyashtornyi, G.Menes, T.Sanzhmyatav, S.Karzhaubai and other scientists conducted researches  &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a name='source_81' class='myref' href='#label_81'&gt;81&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; in 1982-1985. The Mongol-Japanese joint expedition conducted researches  &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a name='source_82' class='myref' href='#label_82'&gt;82&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; in 1996-1998. Japanese scientist Utaka Yoshida was a member of that expedition. His translation was new and distinguished from S.G.Klyashtornyi’s and V.A.Livshits's translations. &#13;
The picture of the stele and a short definition were included in the scientific directory of “Historical and cultural inscriptions of Mongolia”  &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a name='source_83' class='myref' href='#label_83'&gt;83&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. And some photos of the stele were published in 2001 &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a name='source_84' class='myref' href='#label_84'&gt;84&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Kazak scientists conducted researches in 2001, 2002 and 2004  &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a name='source_85' class='myref' href='#label_85'&gt;85&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&#13;
</investigation><details caption="Additional information">Н.Базылхан "Көне түрік бітіктастары мен ескерткіштері (Орхон, Ениесей, Талас)" //"Қазақстан тарихы түркі тілді деректемелерде" атты сериясы бойынша. II том. - Алматы: Дайк-пресс, 2005. - 45-50 б.</details><pdfs caption="Full-text information"><pdf f_author="Баттулга Ц" f_title="Монголын руни бичгийн бага дурсгалууд. Улаанбаатар. - 2005 (1)" f_in="" f_name="mongol1.pdf"/><pdf f_author="Баттулга Ц" f_title="Монголын руни бичгийн бага дурсгалууд. Улаанбаатар. - 2005 (2)" f_in="" f_name="mongol2.pdf"/><pdf f_author="Баттулга Ц" f_title="Монголын руни бичгийн бага дурсгалууд. Улаанбаатар. - 2005 (3)" f_in="" f_name="mongol3.pdf"/></pdfs><refs><ref nm="74">Yutaka Yoshida. Sogdian Part Of Bugut Inscription // Provisional report of researches on historical sites and inscriptions in Mongolia from 1996 to 1998 . Edited by Takao Moriyasu and Ayudai Ochir. The Society of Central Eurasian Studies, Toyonaka, Osaka University, 1999. pp. 122-124.</ref><ref nm="75">Моңғол археологі Ц.Доржсүрэн алғаш тапқан кезде «Бугатын дурсгал (Бұғыт (Бұғылы) ескерткіші)» деп атаған еді. // Ц.Доржсүрэн 1956-1957 онуудад Архангай аймагт археологийн шинжилгээ хийсэн тухай. УБ., 1958.</ref><ref nm="76">Takao Moriyasu, Toshio Hayashi. Site of Bugut // Provisional report of researches on historical sites and inscriptions in Mongolia from 1996 to 1998 . Edited by Takao Moriyasu and Ayudai Ochir. The Society of Central Eurasian Studies, Toyonaka, Osaka University, 1999. pp. 121. ; Войтов В.Е.Древнетюркский пантеон и модель мироздания в культово-поминальных памятниках Монголии VI-VIII в. М., 1996. С.102.</ref><ref nm="77">Ц.Доржсүрэн «1956-1957 онуудад Архангай аймагт археологийн шинжилгээ хийсэн тухай». УБ., 1958. тал 22. // Ц.Доржсүрэн «Археологийн судалгаа. Эрдэм шинжилгээний бүтээлийн эмхэтгэл». Улаанбаатар, 2003, 121 х.</ref><ref nm="78">Сэр-Оджав Н. Археологические памятники Монголии. Современная Монголия. 1960, №7, с.25-28. // Н.Сэр-Оджав Эрдэм шинжилгээний өгүүлэл, илтгэлийн эмхэтгэл. Улаанбаатар хот, 2003, 343 х.</ref><ref nm="79">Ринчэн Б. Монгол нутаг дахь хадны бичээс гэрэлт хөшөөний зѕйл. Corpus Scriptorum Mongolorum. Les pessings pictographiques et les insscriptions sur les pochers et sur les en Mongolie. Tomus.XYI, Fasc.I, Улаанбаатр, 1968. 75-76 –р тал.</ref><ref nm="80">Лившиц В.А., Кляшторный С.Г.Новая согдийская надпись из Монголии, предварительное сообщение //Письменные памятники и проблемы истории культуры народов Востока V. Годичная научная сессия. ЛО ИВ АН.Л., 1969. 51-54 С.; Лившиц В.А.Согдийская надпись из Бугута. ОУМЭ-ийн II их хурал. 1970.1 боть. Улаанбаатар. 1973 .243-250 х.; С.Г.Кляшторный, В.А.Лившиц Согдийская надпись из Бугута. //Страны и народы Востока. М., 1971.С.121-146.; Sergey G. Klyashtorniy-Vladimir A.Livshits The sogdian Inscription of Bugut Revised // Acta Orientalia Academiae Hungaricae XXVI /1.1972. s. 69-102.</ref><ref nm="81">Мэнэс Г. 1982 оны археологийн шинжилгээний тайлан ТХГБС.; Кляшторный С.Г. Советско-Монгольская экспедиция. // Археологическое открытие 1982 года. М., 1984. с. 511-512. ; Т.Санжмятав Архангай аймгийн нутаг дахь эртний түүх соелын дурсгал. Улаанбаатар, 1993, 48, Таблиц-120, 126. ; С.Қаржаубай Орхон мұралары. Астана, 2003, 93-108 б.</ref><ref nm="82">Provisional report of researches on historical sites and inscriptions in Mongolia from 1996 to 1998 . Edited by Takao Moriyasu and Ayudai Ochir. The Society of Central Eurasian Studies, Toyonaka, Osaka University, 1999. pp. 121-125. «Бұғыт ескерткіш кешен»-ді зерттеу экспедиция құрамында Жапониялық Т.Мориясу, Т.Хаяши, Ю.Йошида, А.Катаяма, Т.Осава, моңғолиялық А.Очир, Д.Баяр, Л.Болд, Ц.Баттулга т.б. ғалымдар қатысқан.</ref><ref nm="83">Монгол нутаг дахь түүх соелын дурсгал. Сэдэвчилсэн лавлах .Улаанбаатар, 1999, 206-207 х.</ref><ref nm="84">Mogolistandaki Turk anitlari projesi albumu . TIKA, Ankara, 2001, sayfa 153-164.</ref><ref nm="85">Татпар қаған бітіктасында 2001 жылы С.Е.Әжіғали басқарған экспедициясы, 2002 жылы С.Қаржаубай басқарған экспедициясы, 2004 жылы Н.Базылхан басқарған экспедициясы зерттеу жүргізді. // С.Ажигали Экспедиция в Монголию // Қазақстанның ғылымы мен жоғарғы мектебі №5 (51). 01.03.2003. 6 б.; Қ. Сартқожа Орхон мұралары. Астана, 2003, 34 б.; «Мәдени мұра» мемлекеттік бағдарламасы бойынша 2004 жылы Моңғолияда жүргізілген археографикалық экспедициясының ғылыми есебі. Алматы, 2004 ж.</ref></refs></root>
