<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<root><title>Kul-Chur’s Memorial Complex, The</title><time>731 AD</time><hronology caption="Historical definition">731 ж.</hronology><history>In Old Turkic language: “Küli Čur”. Küli Čur was a military leader of Tardush and had shad-chur title of the Turkic state. No time specified in the text of the monument. Therefore researchers cannot define time of the inscription. But it concerned to the beginning of VIII century.</history><names caption="Names">“Ih Hoshoot”, “The Kul-Chur monument”, “The Kuli-Chur monument”</names><place caption="Places">The memorial complex is located in “Ih-hoshoot” district of Delgerhaan sum in Central aimag, in 200 km southwest from Ulaanbaatar, the capital of Mongolia, at N46º54´ - E104º33´.</place><store>All components of the complex are on its site.</store><general caption="Specification">The memorial complex consists of: &#13;
1. An elevated layer of the ground, 53х35 m &#13;
2. A Stele &#13;
3. A wide pedestal of stele &#13;
4. 8 stone sculptures &#13;
5. 2 lion statues &#13;
6. 2 sheep statues &#13;
7. 4 stone boxes &#13;
8. Balbals (the erected stone sequences) 165 stones last up to 1 km. &#13;
</general><description>The stele is made of dark brown color slate. The inscription on the stele was stored partially. There are 29 lines of Turkic inscription on four sides.</description><size caption="Size">Height of the stele is 1.90 m, width is 0.61 m, height is 0.20 m.</size><investigation caption="Researches">W.Kotwicz studied first and then together with A.N.Samoylovich published translation of the inscription in 1912  &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a name='source_182' class='myref' href='#label_182'&gt;182&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. E.Tryjarski, the member of joint Mongolian-Polish expedition, conducted comprehensive excavation of the memorial complex in 1962. G.Clauson, E.Tryjarski made scientific translation of the inscription in English and published paper copy of the stele and a dictionary in 1971  &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a name='source_183.' class='myref' href='#label_183.'&gt;183.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; H.N.Orhun, S.E.Malov, T.Tekin, G.Aidarov  &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a name='source_184' class='myref' href='#label_184'&gt;184&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and other scientists conducted research of the inscription.&#13;
V.E.Voitov, G.Menes made a plan of the complex and portrayal of the stone sculptures and the stone box in 1983  &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a name='source_185' class='myref' href='#label_185'&gt;185&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Mongolian archeologist D.Bayar examined in detail the stone sculptures and made architectural measurements and scientific characteristics, portrayals  &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a name='source_186' class='myref' href='#label_186'&gt;186&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Kazakh scientists conducted researches in 2001 and 2004.&#13;
</investigation><details caption="Additional information">Н.Базылхан "Көне түрік бітіктастары мен ескерткіштері (Орхон, Ениесей, Талас)" //"Қазақстан тарихы түркі тілді деректемелерде" атты сериясы бойынша. II том. - Алматы: Дайк-пресс, 2005. - Б.119-123.</details><pdfs caption="Full-text information"><pdf f_author="Малов С.Е" f_title="Памятники древнетюркской письменности. Тексты и исследования. – М., Ленинград, Издательствно Академии наук СССР, 1951" f_in="" f_name="Malov_1951.pdf"/><pdf f_author="Малов С.Е" f_title="Образцы древне-турецкой письменности с предисловием и словарем. // Издание восточного факультета САГУ. – Ташкент, 1926." f_in="" f_name="Malov_1921.pdf"/></pdfs><refs><ref nm="182">Kotwicz, W. &amp; A. Samoilovitch Le monument turc d' Ikhe-khuchotu en Mongolie centrale. Rocznik Orientalistyczny, 1928, 4, pp. 60-107.</ref><ref nm="183.">Clauson G. &amp; E. Tryjarski The Inscription at Ikhe Khushotu. Rocznik Orientalistyczny, tom-XXXIV, zeszyt-1, Warszawa, 1971, pp. 7-33, +6 pis.</ref><ref nm="184">Orhun H.N. Eski Turk Yazitlari, Istanbul, 1936, T-1. ss. 135-151.; Малов С.Е.Памятники древнетюркской письменности Монголии и Киргизии. Москва, Ленинград, 1959, С.25-30.; Tekin T. A Grammar of Orkhon Turkic. Indiana university, 1967, pp. 257-258, 293-294.; Айдаров Г.Язык Орхонских памятников древнетюркских письменностей VIII века. Алма-Ата, 1971, С.334-3338 ; Қ. Сартқожаұлы Орхон мұралары (Күүлі-чор киелі орын кешені) Астана, 2003, 226-235, 384-387 б.</ref><ref nm="185">Войтов В.Е.Древнетюркский пантеон и модель мироздания в культово- поминальных памятниках Монголии VI-VIII вв. Москва, 1996, С.22, 28-29, 42. Рис-17.</ref><ref nm="186">Баяр Д.Монголын төв нутаг дахь түрэгийн хүн чулуу. Улаанбатар, 1997 . 86 х, Таблиц- 41-46.</ref></refs></root>
