<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<root><title>inscription the Choir   &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a name='source_192' class='myref' href='#label_192'&gt;192&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;</title><time>732 AD</time><hronology caption="Historical definition">732 ж.</hronology><history>The most southern located among monuments of Orkhon coast.</history><names caption="Names">“The Choir monument”</names><place caption="Places">The stone sculpture was found in barrows on Sansar mountain in 15 km from Choir railway station in Dornogovi aimag of Mongolia at N46º1´ - E109º1´.</place><store>Now the sculpture is an exhibit of the National historical museum of Mongolia.</store><general caption="Specification">The stone sculpture is made from brown granite. The head part of the monument is safe.</general><description>There are 6 lines of inscription on body of the sculpture.</description><size caption="Size">Height is 155 cm, width is 39 cm</size><investigation caption="Researches">Z.Tseveen transferred the sculpture to the museum in Ulaanbaatar in 1929. S.E.Malov  &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a name='source_193' class='myref' href='#label_193'&gt;193&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; published the first translation in 1936. S.G.Klyashtornyi, 1971, O.F.Sertkaya, 1998 conducted researches of the inscription  &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a name='source_194' class='myref' href='#label_194'&gt;194&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Kazakh expeditions conducted researches in 2001 and 2004.</investigation><details caption="Additional information">Н.Базылхан "Көне түрік бітіктастары мен ескерткіштері (Орхон, Ениесей, Талас)" //"Қазақстан тарихы түркі тілді деректемелерде" атты сериясы бойынша. II том. - Алматы: Дайк-пресс, 2005. - Б.126-127.</details><pdfs caption="Full-text information"><pdf f_author="Ph.Denwood " f_title="Recently Found Relics of Turkic Stone Sculpture from the Territory of the Mongolian People&amp;apos;s Republic" f_in="In: Ph.Denwood (ed.), Arts of the Eurasian Steppelands, London, pp. 203-217, +3 pis. " f_name="415.pdf"/><pdf f_author="Васильев Д.Д" f_title="Памятники тюркской рунической письменности азиатского ареала." f_in="Советская тюркология, 1976. – № 1. – С.71-81." f_name="Vasilev_1976.pdf"/><pdf f_author="Баттулга Ц" f_title="Монголын руни бичгийн бага дурсгалууд. Улаанбаатар. - 2005 (1)" f_in="" f_name="mongol1.pdf"/><pdf f_author="Баттулга Ц" f_title="Монголын руни бичгийн бага дурсгалууд. Улаанбаатар. - 2005 (2)" f_in="" f_name="mongol2.pdf"/><pdf f_author="Баттулга Ц" f_title="Монголын руни бичгийн бага дурсгалууд. Улаанбаатар. - 2005 (3)" f_in="" f_name="mongol3.pdf"/></pdfs><refs><ref nm="192">Бәдізге түрік бітік мәтін қашалған бұдан басқа тағы бір дана ескерткіш бар. Ол Енисей бойынан табылған Е-37 (Тес).</ref><ref nm="193">Малов С.Е.Новые памятники с турецскими рунами // Язык и мышление ИЯ имени Н.Я.Марра АН СССР. Ленинград, 1936, № VI-VII, С.251-259.</ref><ref nm="194">Orhun H.N. Eski Turk Yazitlari (Bir baba yaziti), Istanbul, 1939, T-2. ss. 164-168.; Tryjarski E. The Present State of Preservation of Old Turkic Relics in Mongolia and the Need for their Conservation // Ural-Altaische Jahrbucher, 1966, 38, рр. 158-173. ; Ринчэн Б.Монгол нутаг дахь хадны бичээс гэрэлт хөшөөний зүйл. Corpus Scriptorum Mongolorum. Les pessings pictographiques et les insscriptions sur les pochers et sur les en Mongolie. Tomus. XYI, Fasc.I, Улаанбаатар, 1968. 39 –р тал. ; Кляшторный С.Г.Руническая надпись из восточеой Гоби // Studia Turcica, Budapest 1971, pp. 249-258. Кляшторный С.Г.Руническая надпись на каменном извание из Чойрена // Страны и народы Востока, XXII, Москва, 1980, С.90-102. ; Sertkaya O.F. Čoyr yaziti, Orkun, Turkce Dergi. Sayi-5, temmuz,1998, s.33-38.; Sertkaya O.F. Gökturk harfli Čoyr yaziti /www.turan.tc/kalem/ ss.1-11. &#13;
	Аталмыш зерттеулердің ішінде бұл бәдіз бітік мәтінінің таңба-әріптерін неғұрлым дұрыс белгілеп аударған түркиялық ғалым О.Ф.Серткая, ол өзінің зерттеу еңбегінде: «Tulku bitidim ïrq aygïl baŋa adïrïlmaz tat bardï Tun Jigen Irkin Tun Bilge šad Iltitis qaganqa ičikin üčünč ay yiti qa ögünil sebini barïrïgïz» деп транскрипциясын түзеп «Тас баба үстіне жаздым, бал ашып сөйле маған, бір бірінен айырылмаған жат болмаған кезде Тұн Йеген Іркін, Тұн Білге шад Ілтіріс қағанға бағын! Үшінші ай жетінде сүйенішпен барыңыз» деп аударған.</ref></refs></root>
