<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<root><title>Huis Tolgoy Memorial Complex, The</title><time>VI-VII centuries</time><hronology caption="Historical definition">581-582 ж.</hronology><history>There is no clue found yet to read both Brahmi (old Sanskrit) and “kharoshti-like” inscriptions. Therefore it is still unknown the time of the complex and the person it has been devoted to. &#13;
According to The Tatpar (Kutlug) kagan inscription, “Maga Umna kagan ordered to erect a stone of law for (his) father Maga Tatpar kagan...”. So these remains could be of those stones of law.</history><names caption="Names">“Huis Tolgoyn dursgal”, “The Huis Tolagay stele”.</names><place caption="Places">Found in district «Huis Tolgoy» of Mogod sum in Bulgan aimag of Mongolia, N48º´– E103º´.&#13;
&#13;
</place><store>Both steles are stored in the laboratory warehouse of Archeology institute of Mongolian Academy of Sciences.</store><general caption="Specification">The complex includes stone clusters, 8 stone boxes and two steles. There are no balbal stones (the erected stone sequence) in this memorial complex.</general><description>Two monolingual inscriptions had written in brahmi – old Sanskrit  (unknown language).</description><size caption="Size">Height of the first stele is 1.54 m, width is 0.41 m, and thickness is 0.12-0.15 m. Height of the second stele is 1.61 m, width is 0.40-0.44 m and thickness is 0.19-0.21 m.</size><investigation caption="Researches">The stele is found by Mongolian archeologist D.Navaan &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a name='source_88' class='myref' href='#label_88'&gt;88&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; in 1975. K.Sartkozha published the general description of the complex in 1984. And he published a picture and description of the first stele in his book “The Orkhon heritages” &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a name='source_89' class='myref' href='#label_89'&gt;89&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; in 2003.</investigation><details caption="Additional information">Н.Базылхан "Көне түрік бітіктастары мен ескерткіштері (Орхон, Ениесей, Талас)" //"Қазақстан тарихы түркі тілді деректемелерде" атты сериясы бойынша. II том. - Алматы: Дайк-пресс, 2005. - Б.51.</details><pdfs caption="Full-text information"/><refs><ref nm="88">Д.Наваан 1976 оны хээрийн шинжилгээний тайлан ТХГБС</ref><ref nm="89">Сартқожа Қ. Орхон мұралары. Астана, 2003, 92-93 б.</ref></refs></root>
