<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<root><title>Inscription  Ordu-balyq II (Karabalghasun II) </title><time>IX century</time><hronology caption="Historical definition">IX ғ</hronology><history>М .Шинэхүүдiң пiкiрiнше, қытай жылнамасы «Тан-шу» да аталатын Ұйғыр қағандығының IX ғасырда өмір сүрген қолбасшысы «Гюйлу-Мохэ» деген кiсi осы Бұқа болу керек.</history><names caption="Names">“The Khar Balgas monument”</names><place caption="Places">The stele was found on coast of the river Zharantain in 8 km north of Ordu-balyk city, which is located in west of Orkhon river in Hotont sum of Arkhangai aimag.</place><store>Now it is placed in the square of building of Social sciences of Mongolian Academy of Sciences.</store><general caption="Specification"></general><description>The stele is made of grey granite. There are 12 lines of inscription.</description><size caption="Size">Height – 1.7 m, width – 0.30-0.25 m, thickness – 0.12-0.15 m.</size><investigation caption="Researches">The stele is found by S.Myagmarzhav, the school teacher of history in 1973. The Soviet-Mongolian expedition transferred the stele to laboratory of History Institute of Academy of Sciences in 1975. Mongolian scientist M.Shinehuu examined the inscription for the first time  &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a name='source_232' class='myref' href='#label_232'&gt;232&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Kazakh scientists conducted researches in 2001 and 2004.</investigation><details caption="Additional information">Н.Базылхан "Көне түрік бітіктастары мен ескерткіштері (Орхон, Ениесей, Талас)" //"Қазақстан тарихы түркі тілді деректемелерде" атты сериясы бойынша. II том. - Алматы: Дайк-пресс, 2005. - Б.152-153.</details><pdfs caption="Full-text information"/><refs><ref nm="232">Шинэхүү М.Новый памятник рунической письменности уйгурского Карабалгасуна // Олон Улсын Монголч Эрдэмтний III их хурал, Боть-3, Улаанбаатар, 1979, 301-305 т. ; Шинэхүү М.Орхон-Сэлэнгийн руни бичгийн шинэ дурсгал // Археологийн Судлал, Studio Archaeologica Instituti Historiae Academiae Scientiarum Reipublicae Populi Mongolici. Tomus- 8, Fasc. 1, Улаанбаатар, 1980, 42-43 х.	&#13;
Сондай-ақ хабарлама ретінде мына мәліметтер жарияланды: Санжмятав Т.Архангай аймагийн нутаг дахь эртний түүх соёлын дурсгал. Улаанбаатар. 1993, 50-т., Таблица-128. ; Болд Л.БНМАУ-ын нутаг дахь хадны бичээс. Улаанбаатар, 1990, 126-127 т.; Цэвээндорж, Д.Уйгурын ХаантУлсын үеийн бичигтэй хөшөөд. Археологийн Судлал, (SA,Tom. 15, Fasc. 1-11), Улаанбаатар, 1995, 70-72т.</ref></refs></root>
