<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<root><title>Mainz 388 (TM 326)  &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a name='source_408' class='myref' href='#label_408'&gt;408&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;</title><time>Орта ғасырдың басы.</time><hronology caption="Historical definition"></hronology><history></history><names caption="Names">Mainz 388 (TM 326)</names><place caption="Places"></place><store>Берлиндегі Бранденбург ғылым академиясында (Berlin-Brandenburgischen Akademie der Wissenschaften) сақтаулы.</store><general caption="Specification">The top part of the manuscript with well-preserved left edge.</general><description>Manuscript: Old Turkic, little bit turned pale.&#13;
Paper: firm, chestnut&#13;
Quantity of lines: 8 lines in each and one line of heading on both sides.&#13;
Designations: on the front at the top: Т.М.326 (pencil); on the left bottom corner stickers ТМ 326 and Mainz 388.&#13;
Characteristics: colon marks are outlined in red; in back the color of heading is red.&#13;
</description><size caption="Size">Distance between lines: 0.9 cm; between heading and the first line: 2.1 cm.&#13;
10.7 cm (height) x 11.7 cm (width).&#13;
</size><investigation caption="Researches">L.Clark  &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a name='source_422' class='myref' href='#label_422'&gt;422&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; claims that this fragment is a part of the story “Mentions, merchant, slave, astrology”. А.Lе Coq  &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a name='source_425' class='myref' href='#label_425'&gt;425&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, V.Thomsen  &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a name='source_451' class='myref' href='#label_451'&gt;451&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; conducted researches.</investigation><details caption="Additional information">Depositum der BERLIN-BRANDENBURGISCHEN AKADEMIE DER WISSENSCHAFTEN in der STAATSBIBLIOTHEK ZU BERLIN - Preussischer Kulturbesitz. Orientabteilung.</details><pdfs caption="Full-text information"><pdf f_author="" f_title="Konkordanz der in Katalogen beschriebenen Mainz-Fragmente. Stand: 11.08.2005" f_in="" f_name="VOHD_Mainz_neu.pdf"/><pdf f_author="Wilkens J" f_title="Alttürkische handschriften. Teil 8. Manichäeisch-turkische texte der Berliner Turfansammlung." f_in="" f_name="412.pdf"/><pdf f_author="Clark L" f_title="Chapter III. The Turkic Manichaean Literature." f_in="Emerging from darkness. Studies in the Recovery of Manichaean Sources. Nag Hammadi and Manichaean Studies." f_name="Nag_Hammadi_and_Mahichaean.pdf"/><pdf f_author="Sertkaya O.F" f_title="Fragmente in alttürkischer Runenschrift aus den Turfan-Funden." f_in="Runen, Tamgas und Graffiti aus Asien und Osteuropa. 1985." f_name="Runen_Tamgas_und_Graffiti.pdf"/></pdfs><refs><ref nm="408">Alttürkische Handschriften. Teil 8: Manichäisch-türkische Texte der Berliner Turfansammlung. Beschrieben von JENS WILKENS. Stuttgart 2000. (Verzeichnis der Orientalischen Handschriften in Deutschland. 13,16.) BAND XIII, 16.</ref><ref nm="422">Clark, Larry: The Turkic Manichaean Literature. In: Emerging from Darkness. Studies in the Recovery of Manichaean Sources. Edd. Paul Mirecki und Jason BeDuhn. Leiden/New York/Köln 1997. 89-141.</ref><ref nm="425">Le Coq, Albert von: Köktürkisches aus Turfan (Manuscriptfragmente in köktürkischen "Runen" aus Toyoq und Idiqut Schähri). SPAW. Phil.-hist. Kl. 1909. 1047-1061.</ref><ref nm="451">Thomsen V.  Dr. M. A. Stein’s manuscrifts  in Turkish “ runic” scrift from Miran and Tun-Huang // Journal of the Royal Asiatic Society, London, 1912. Р. 181–227;   Thomsen V. Еin Blatt in turkischer “runen” schrift aus Turfan // Sitzungsberichte der Preussischen Akademie der Wissenschaften. Phil.-hist. 1910. XV;  Thomsen V. Fragments of a runic Turkish manuscript Kao 0107 from Kara-Khova // Innermost Asia, Vol. II. Oxford, 1928.</ref></refs></root>
