<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<root><title>U 172 (T II D 67)  &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a name='source_408' class='myref' href='#label_408'&gt;408&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;</title><time>Орта ғасырдың басы.</time><hronology caption="Historical definition"></hronology><history></history><names caption="Names">U 172 (T II D 67)</names><place caption="Places">Found during the archeological excavations of the Second German Turfan expedition (Zweite Preußische Turfanexpedition  &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a name='source_410' class='myref' href='#label_410'&gt;410&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;) in East Turkestan.</place><store>Берлиндегі Бранденбург ғылым академиясында (Berlin-Brandenburgischen Akademie der Wissenschaften) сақтаулы.</store><general caption="Specification">The top part of a double page manuscript.</general><description>Manuscript: Old Turkic.&#13;
Paper: fragile, grey-beige, spotty.&#13;
Quantity of lines: on both sides 1 line in each and one line of heading separated by florets.&#13;
Designations: B: between heading and the first line: T II (stamp) and D67 (pencil); A: on the left top corner the old sticker T II D67 and on the right top corner a sticker U 172.&#13;
Characteristics: red outlines of a colon marks are slight; headings are dark blue color; part I: florets with red petals and with black center; part II: florets with red petals and with blue center.&#13;
</description><size caption="Size">Distance between lines: part I (on the right): A: between heading and the first line: 2.0 cm; part II (at the left): 1.7 cm.&#13;
4.5 cm (height) x 9.0 cm (width).&#13;
</size><investigation caption="Researches">Sertkaya  &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a name='source_424' class='myref' href='#label_424'&gt;424&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; conducted researches.</investigation><details caption="Additional information">Depositum der BERLIN-BRANDENBURGISCHEN AKADEMIE DER WISSENSCHAFTEN in der STAATSBIBLIOTHEK ZU BERLIN - Preussischer Kulturbesitz. Orientabteilung.</details><pdfs caption="Full-text information"><pdf f_author="" f_title="Konkordanz der in Katalogen beschriebenen Mainz-Fragmente. Stand: 11.08.2005" f_in="" f_name="VOHD_Mainz_neu.pdf"/><pdf f_author="Wilkens J" f_title="Alttürkische handschriften. Teil 8. Manichäeisch-turkische texte der Berliner Turfansammlung." f_in="" f_name="412.pdf"/><pdf f_author="Clark L" f_title="Chapter III. The Turkic Manichaean Literature." f_in="Emerging from darkness. Studies in the Recovery of Manichaean Sources. Nag Hammadi and Manichaean Studies." f_name="Nag_Hammadi_and_Mahichaean.pdf"/><pdf f_author="Sertkaya O.F" f_title="Fragmente in alttürkischer Runenschrift aus den Turfan-Funden." f_in="Runen, Tamgas und Graffiti aus Asien und Osteuropa. 1985." f_name="Runen_Tamgas_und_Graffiti.pdf"/></pdfs><refs><ref nm="408">Alttürkische Handschriften. Teil 8: Manichäisch-türkische Texte der Berliner Turfansammlung. Beschrieben von JENS WILKENS. Stuttgart 2000. (Verzeichnis der Orientalischen Handschriften in Deutschland. 13,16.) BAND XIII, 16.</ref><ref nm="410">Екінші Прусс Тұрпан экспедициясы. Бұл экспедицияда жүргізілген қазбаларда табылған қолжазбаларды TII деп белгілеген. Экспедицияны Dr. A. v. Le Coq бастап барған. Th. Bartus қатысқан. Үрімшіден бастап Тұрпан оазисіне дейін (Хошо және соны қоршап жатқан аймақ, Жар-Қото, 1904 жыл, қарашадан бастап 1905 жылдың тамызына дейін; Хами 1905 жылдың тамызы; Тұрпан). Барлығы 103 түйіншек әкетілген. Олардың ішінде дені сурет (Bäzäklik), мәтіндер көп емес. &#13;
&#13;
TII - Zweite Preußische Turfanexpedition&#13;
&#13;
Expedition. Leiter: Dr. A. v. Le Coq; Teilnehmer: Th. Bartus. Route: Urumči -Turfanoase (Qočo und umliegende Stätten, Yar-Khoto Nov.1904-Aug.1905; Hami Aug. 1905; Turfan) - nördl. Seidenstraße-Kašghar (Okt. 1905; dort Vereinigung im Dez. mit 3. Expedition). 103 Kisten, hauptsächlich Gemälde (Bäzäklik), weniger Texte (christl. Texte in syr., sogd., mp., uig.; buddh. Texte).</ref><ref nm="424">Sertkaya, Osman Fikri: Fragmente in alttürkischer Runnenschrift aus den Turfan-Funden. In: Runnen, Tamgas und Grafitti aus Asien und Osteuropa. Edd. Klaus Röhrborn und Wolfgang Veenker. Wiesbaden 1985 VdSUA 1985, 133-164. [reprint mit weiteren Faksimiles in: Göktürk Tarihinin Meseleleri. Probleme der köktürkischen Geschichte. Some problems of köktürk history. Ankara 1995. 255-276]</ref></refs></root>
