<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<root><title>T II T 14  &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a name='source_408' class='myref' href='#label_408'&gt;408&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;</title><time>Орта ғасырдың басы.</time><hronology caption="Historical definition"></hronology><history></history><names caption="Names">T II T 14</names><place caption="Places">Шығыс Түркістан. Екінші Прусс Тұрпан экспедициясында (Zweite Preußische Turfanexpedition  &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a name='source_410' class='myref' href='#label_410'&gt;410&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;) жүргізілген қазба жұмыстарында табылған.</place><store>The fragment is lost.</store><general caption="Specification">Көне түрікше, артқы жағы қытайша мәтіні бар жұмсақ, сары қоңыр түсті, талшықты, су тиген дақтары бар қағаз беті.&#13;
</general><description>Manuscript: front in Old Turkic, back in Chinese.&#13;
Paper: soft, tan, fibrous, with aqueous stains.&#13;
Quantity of lines: 31 lines in front.&#13;
Characteristics: the majority of lines consist of two letters.  The word "taš" in line 30 written with greater symbols.&#13;
</description><size caption="Size">25.0 cm (height) x 13.3 cm (width).</size><investigation caption="Researches">V.Thomsen  &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a name='source_594' class='myref' href='#label_594'&gt;594&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; conducted researches. L.Clark &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a name='source_422' class='myref' href='#label_422'&gt;422&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; claims that is the fragment of "Qualities of Five Precious Stones".</investigation><details caption="Additional information">Depositum der BERLIN-BRANDENBURGISCHEN AKADEMIE DER WISSENSCHAFTEN in der STAATSBIBLIOTHEK ZU BERLIN - Preussischer Kulturbesitz. Orientabteilung.</details><pdfs caption="Full-text information"><pdf f_author="" f_title="Konkordanz der in Katalogen beschriebenen Mainz-Fragmente. Stand: 11.08.2005" f_in="" f_name="VOHD_Mainz_neu.pdf"/><pdf f_author="Wilkens J" f_title="Alttürkische handschriften. Teil 8. Manichäeisch-turkische texte der Berliner Turfansammlung." f_in="" f_name="412.pdf"/><pdf f_author="Clark L" f_title="Chapter III. The Turkic Manichaean Literature." f_in="Emerging from darkness. Studies in the Recovery of Manichaean Sources. Nag Hammadi and Manichaean Studies." f_name="Nag_Hammadi_and_Mahichaean.pdf"/><pdf f_author="Sertkaya O.F" f_title="Fragmente in alttürkischer Runenschrift aus den Turfan-Funden." f_in="Runen, Tamgas und Graffiti aus Asien und Osteuropa. 1985." f_name="Runen_Tamgas_und_Graffiti.pdf"/></pdfs><refs><ref nm="408">Alttürkische Handschriften. Teil 8: Manichäisch-türkische Texte der Berliner Turfansammlung. Beschrieben von JENS WILKENS. Stuttgart 2000. (Verzeichnis der Orientalischen Handschriften in Deutschland. 13,16.) BAND XIII, 16.</ref><ref nm="410">Екінші Прусс Тұрпан экспедициясы. Бұл экспедицияда жүргізілген қазбаларда табылған қолжазбаларды TII деп белгілеген. Экспедицияны Dr. A. v. Le Coq бастап барған. Th. Bartus қатысқан. Үрімшіден бастап Тұрпан оазисіне дейін (Хошо және соны қоршап жатқан аймақ, Жар-Қото, 1904 жыл, қарашадан бастап 1905 жылдың тамызына дейін; Хами 1905 жылдың тамызы; Тұрпан). Барлығы 103 түйіншек әкетілген. Олардың ішінде дені сурет (Bäzäklik), мәтіндер көп емес. &#13;
&#13;
TII - Zweite Preußische Turfanexpedition&#13;
&#13;
Expedition. Leiter: Dr. A. v. Le Coq; Teilnehmer: Th. Bartus. Route: Urumči -Turfanoase (Qočo und umliegende Stätten, Yar-Khoto Nov.1904-Aug.1905; Hami Aug. 1905; Turfan) - nördl. Seidenstraße-Kašghar (Okt. 1905; dort Vereinigung im Dez. mit 3. Expedition). 103 Kisten, hauptsächlich Gemälde (Bäzäklik), weniger Texte (christl. Texte in syr., sogd., mp., uig.; buddh. Texte).</ref><ref nm="594">Кубарев Г.В. Культура древних тюрок Алтая. По материалам погребальных памятников. - Новосибирск, 2005.</ref><ref nm="422">Clark, Larry: The Turkic Manichaean Literature. In: Emerging from Darkness. Studies in the Recovery of Manichaean Sources. Edd. Paul Mirecki und Jason BeDuhn. Leiden/New York/Köln 1997. 89-141.</ref></refs></root>
