<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<root><title>Mainz 385a-d (TM 337)  &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a name='source_408' class='myref' href='#label_408'&gt;408&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;</title><time>Орта ғасырдың басы.</time><hronology caption="Historical definition"></hronology><history></history><names caption="Names">Mainz 385a-d (TM 337)</names><place caption="Places"></place><store>Берлиндегі Бранденбург ғылым академиясында (Berlin-Brandenburgischen Akademie der Wissenschaften) сақтаулы.</store><general caption="Specification">4 fragments are glazed together.&#13;
a (at the left): left field is 1.9 cm; b (on the right, top): the right part of the manuscript, the letter slightly turned pale, right field is 1.3 cm; c and d: average parts of the manuscript, the last fragment is damaged.&#13;
</general><description>Manuscript: Old Turkic.&#13;
Paper: aqueous stains.&#13;
Quantity of lines: a: 7 lines in each in A and B; b: 3 lines in each in A and B; c: 3 lines in each in A and B; d: 2 lines in each only with one symbol in A and B.&#13;
Designations: A: a: on a right edge: Т.М. 337 (pencil); c: on the bottom:  Т.М.337 (pencil); on the bottom stickers Mainz 385 and TM. 337.&#13;
Characteristics: Colon marks are outlined in red. In the fragment “b” colon marks are not outlined in red, put down on one red point on the right and on the left of colon marks.&#13;
</description><size caption="Size">Distance between lines: a: 1.1 cm; b: 0.8 cm; c: 1.0 cm; d: it is not defined.&#13;
a: 7.7 cm (height) x 5.1 cm (width); b: 5.4 cm (height) x 3.1 cm (width); c: 2.8 cm (height) x 3.8 cm (width); d: 1.4 cm (height) x 0.8 cm (width).&#13;
</size><investigation caption="Researches">Sertkaya  &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a name='source_424' class='myref' href='#label_424'&gt;424&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; conducted researches.</investigation><details caption="Additional information">Depositum der BERLIN-BRANDENBURGISCHEN AKADEMIE DER WISSENSCHAFTEN in der STAATSBIBLIOTHEK ZU BERLIN - Preussischer Kulturbesitz. Orientabteilung.</details><pdfs caption="Full-text information"><pdf f_author="" f_title="Konkordanz der in Katalogen beschriebenen Mainz-Fragmente. Stand: 11.08.2005" f_in="" f_name="VOHD_Mainz_neu.pdf"/><pdf f_author="Wilkens J" f_title="Alttürkische handschriften. Teil 8. Manichäeisch-turkische texte der Berliner Turfansammlung." f_in="" f_name="412.pdf"/><pdf f_author="Clark L" f_title="Chapter III. The Turkic Manichaean Literature." f_in="Emerging from darkness. Studies in the Recovery of Manichaean Sources. Nag Hammadi and Manichaean Studies." f_name="Nag_Hammadi_and_Mahichaean.pdf"/><pdf f_author="Sertkaya O.F" f_title="Fragmente in alttürkischer Runenschrift aus den Turfan-Funden." f_in="Runen, Tamgas und Graffiti aus Asien und Osteuropa. 1985." f_name="Runen_Tamgas_und_Graffiti.pdf"/></pdfs><refs><ref nm="408">Alttürkische Handschriften. Teil 8: Manichäisch-türkische Texte der Berliner Turfansammlung. Beschrieben von JENS WILKENS. Stuttgart 2000. (Verzeichnis der Orientalischen Handschriften in Deutschland. 13,16.) BAND XIII, 16.</ref><ref nm="424">Sertkaya, Osman Fikri: Fragmente in alttürkischer Runnenschrift aus den Turfan-Funden. In: Runnen, Tamgas und Grafitti aus Asien und Osteuropa. Edd. Klaus Röhrborn und Wolfgang Veenker. Wiesbaden 1985 VdSUA 1985, 133-164. [reprint mit weiteren Faksimiles in: Göktürk Tarihinin Meseleleri. Probleme der köktürkischen Geschichte. Some problems of köktürk history. Ankara 1995. 255-276]</ref></refs></root>
