<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<root><title>Mainz 169a,b+c,d (T I)</title><time>Орта ғасырдың басы.</time><hronology caption="Historical definition"></hronology><history>The beginning of the Middle Ages.</history><names caption="Names">Mainz 169a,b+c,d (T I)</names><place caption="Places">Found during the archeological excavations in the First German Turfan expedition (Erste Preußische Turfanexpedition  &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a name='source_409' class='myref' href='#label_409'&gt;409&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;) in East Turkestan.</place><store>It is kept in the Berlin-Brandenburg Academy of Sciences (Berlin-Brandenburgischen Akademie der Wissenschaften).</store><general caption="Specification">4 fragments are glazed together and 3 (a-c) of them are parts of one manuscript.</general><description>[Manuscript: Old Turkic.&#13;
Paper: a-c: dense, smooth, yellow; d: dense, ink is water damaged.&#13;
Quantity of lines: a: 3 lines in each in A and B; b+c: 4 lines in each in A and B; d: 4 lines in each in A and B, but the text in A is completely indistinct.&#13;
Designations: B: a: on edge TI (pencil); c: on a right edge TI (pencil); d: on edge TI (pencil); A: at the top left corner there are stickers Mainz 169 and TI x 21. &#13;
Characteristics: Colon marks are outlined in red; B: a: Uig. italics in a left edge: yükü(nč); b-c: uig. italics in a left edge: ...] nom ...&#13;
</description><size caption="Size">Distance between lines: 0.8 cm. &#13;
a: 3.1 cm (height) x 4.2 cm (width); b: 3.2 cm (height) x 6.0 cm (width); c: 2.8 cm (height) x 3.1 cm (width); d: 3.4 cm (height) x 3.8 cm (width).&#13;
</size><investigation caption="Researches">Sertkaya  &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a name='source_424' class='myref' href='#label_424'&gt;424&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; considers, that the fragment “a” is the left top part of the fragment “b”. Joining them together it is possible to read 4 lines. Also he considers that all fragments are middle parts, only the fragment “a” is the bottom right edge of a page of the manuscript.</investigation><details caption="Additional information">Depositum der BERLIN-BRANDENBURGISCHEN AKADEMIE DER WISSENSCHAFTEN in der STAATSBIBLIOTHEK ZU BERLIN - Preussischer Kulturbesitz. Orientabteilung. Mainz 169a,b+c,d (T I).&#13;
</details><pdfs caption="Full-text information"><pdf f_author="" f_title="Konkordanz der in Katalogen beschriebenen Mainz-Fragmente. Stand: 11.08.2005" f_in="" f_name="VOHD_Mainz_neu.pdf"/><pdf f_author="Wilkens J" f_title="Alttürkische handschriften. Teil 8. Manichäeisch-turkische texte der Berliner Turfansammlung." f_in="" f_name="412.pdf"/><pdf f_author="Clark L" f_title="Chapter III. The Turkic Manichaean Literature." f_in="Emerging from darkness. Studies in the Recovery of Manichaean Sources. Nag Hammadi and Manichaean Studies." f_name="Nag_Hammadi_and_Mahichaean.pdf"/><pdf f_author="Sertkaya O.F" f_title="Fragmente in alttürkischer Runenschrift aus den Turfan-Funden." f_in="Runen, Tamgas und Graffiti aus Asien und Osteuropa. 1985." f_name="Runen_Tamgas_und_Graffiti.pdf"/></pdfs><refs><ref nm="409">Бірінші Прусс Тұрпан экспедициясы. Осы экспедицияда жүргізілген қазбаларда табылған қолжазбаларды TI деп белгілеген. &#13;
&#13;
TI Erste Preußische Turfanexpedition.&#13;
&#13;
Expedition. Leiter: Prof. A. Grünwedel; Teilnehmer: Dr. G. Huth, Th. Bartus. Route: Kulja-Urumči-Turfanoase (Qočo, Bäzäklik, Sängim, Toyuq Nov. 1902 - März 1903 [Gemälde, Statuen, mir./uig./np. Manuskripte der Manichäer in man./uig./Runenschrift, ind./chin./tang. Texte]) - nördl. Seidenstraße (Toqsun-Qarašahr-Kuča-Ruinen bei Qumtura [Gemälde] - Qïzïl-Aq-su-Tumšuq-Maralbaši-Kašghar). 46 Kisten von Fundstücken.</ref><ref nm="424">Sertkaya, Osman Fikri: Fragmente in alttürkischer Runnenschrift aus den Turfan-Funden. In: Runnen, Tamgas und Grafitti aus Asien und Osteuropa. Edd. Klaus Röhrborn und Wolfgang Veenker. Wiesbaden 1985 VdSUA 1985, 133-164. [reprint mit weiteren Faksimiles in: Göktürk Tarihinin Meseleleri. Probleme der köktürkischen Geschichte. Some problems of köktürk history. Ankara 1995. 255-276]</ref></refs></root>
