<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<root><title>Baryk IV (e-8)</title><time></time><hronology caption="Historical definition"></hronology><history></history><names caption="Names">Барык IV, Е 8</names><place caption="Places">One of 6 monuments erected on hillock on 11 km to the south from village Iji-tal at left coast of the river Baryk (in 60 km below the mouth of river Elegest) by specification of Batmanov. Е 5 and Е 8 were erected side by side, in 300 m south of Е 6, Е 7 an a stele without inscriptions. There was one more stele in the same place without inscriptions, but with a sign.</place><store>The Baryk IV (e-8) delivered to the Tyva museum in 1961.</store><general caption="Specification">Flat stele, red-brown sandstone, in section - strongly extended rectangular, poor traces of polishing.</general><description>There are 3 lines of text and a sign. Due to destructions of the surface the texts is almost non-readable.</description><size caption="Size">Height – 115 cm, length – 53 cm, width – 12 cm</size><investigation caption="Researches">D.Klements found in 1891. Four steles were found by D.Klements in 1891 (circumstances and descriptions of findings are in the Explanatory note of D.Klements in Introduction to the second issue of Radloff’s Atlas  &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a name='source_122' class='myref' href='#label_122'&gt;122&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;).&#13;
Found again in 1961 by Batmanov (with help of Tulush) and delivered by researchers of Tyva museum and Tyva Scientific and Research Institute of Language, Literature and History (ТНИИЯЛИ) to the Tyva museum.&#13;
S.E.Malov  &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a name='source_507' class='myref' href='#label_507'&gt;507&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, I.Batmanov, I.Kormushin &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a name='source_270' class='myref' href='#label_270'&gt;270&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and others investigated.</investigation><details caption="Additional information">И.В.Кормушинның оқуы:&#13;
1. … kün aj: bökmedim-e&#13;
2.  ... /quj/da: qunčyïmqa: adïrïltïm&#13;
3. …jegin ben … &#13;
&#13;
Солнце луна, - я не насладился (вами)&#13;
С моими супругами в (женских покоях) я разлучился&#13;
Я ..йегин..</details><pdfs caption="Full-text information"><pdf f_author="Васильев Д.Д" f_title="Памятники тюркской рунической письменности азиатского ареала." f_in="Советская тюркология, 1976. – № 1. – С.71-81." f_name="Vasilev_1976.pdf"/></pdfs><refs><ref nm="122">Radloff W. Atlas der Alterthümer der Mongolei. Arbeiten der Orchon Expedition. I-IV. St.Petersburg, 1892, 1893, 1896, 1899. ; Радлов В.В.Атлас древностей Монголии. Труды Орхонской экспедиции, I-IV. СПб., 1892, 1893, 1896, 1899.</ref><ref nm="507">Кызласов Л.Р. О датировке памятников енисейской письменности. - СА, 1965, № 3, С.39</ref><ref nm="270">Кормушин И.В.Тюркские Енисейские эпитафии. Тексты и исследования. М., 1997. С.5.</ref></refs></root>
