<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<root><title>Chaa-Hol VI (e-18)</title><time></time><hronology caption="Historical definition"></hronology><history></history><names caption="Names">Чаа-Холь VI, Е 18</names><place caption="Places">Monuments of this group were found in a valley near the river Chaa-Hol, the left inflow of Ulug-Hem, in 25 km above the mouth of river Hemchik. This district is on the bottom of water basin Sayano-Shushenskii now. All monuments of the group, except Е 15, are in museum exhibitions.&#13;
E 18 was found in the district on left coast of the river Chaa-Hol in 8 km from its mouth.</place><store>The stone is delivered to the Tyva museum in 1961.</store><general caption="Specification">The stela is made of gray-green slate. Oval in section. The surface is roughly squared. Covered with cracks and considerably destroyed by aeration.&#13;
</general><description>The epitaph in 5 lines is written vertically on two sides. Direction of reading of lines I to IV from left to right, the line V from right to left. There are asymmetric signs in lines I-IV.&#13;
</description><size caption="Size">Height – 98 cm, length – 39 cm, width – 16 cm</size><investigation caption="Researches">Aspelin found in 1888 following the message of Safyanov. Heikel made photo of the stele in 1889. Oshurkov made a copy and transferred it to Radloff. Radloff (ATIM, P. 322) wrote that the stele was found near "the first Chaa-hol monument". However according of hid designation it is clear that he meant "the second" - UTsch. I (see the Index). It is proved also by Radloff's definition of the monument UTsch. VI. Some editions wrongly point the found place of  Е 18 as "near the Chaa-hol I". &#13;
Investigated S.E.Malov, H.N.Orkun, etc.&#13;
</investigation><details caption="Additional information"></details><pdfs caption="Full-text information"><pdf f_author="Васильев Д.Д" f_title="Памятники тюркской рунической письменности азиатского ареала." f_in="Советская тюркология, 1976. – № 1. – С.71-81." f_name="Vasilev_1976.pdf"/></pdfs><refs/></root>
