<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<root><title>Chaa-Hol V (e-17)</title><time></time><hronology caption="Historical definition"></hronology><history></history><names caption="Names">Чаа-Холь V, Е 17</names><place caption="Places">Monuments of this group were found in a valley near the river Chaa-Hol, the left inflow of Ulug-Hem, in 25 km above the mouth of river Hemchik. This district is on the bottom of water basin Sayano-Shushenskii now. All monuments of the group, except Е 15, are in museum exhibitions.&#13;
E 17 was found in district on left coast of the river Chaa-Hol in 8 km from its mouth.</place><store>The stele is delivered to Kyzyl by researchers of  Sayan-Tyva expedition (СТЭАН) and transferred in the Tyva Museum in 1973.</store><general caption="Specification">The stele is made of light grey slate. Split on two parts.</general><description>The inscription of 3 lines is located vertically on two sides. There is a tamga below the line 1. There are different symbols  below lines 2 and 3 made using another technic, probably, tamgas. Lines 2 and 3 on narrow sides are strictly linear and differ from the 1st line.&#13;
</description><size caption="Size">Height – 159 cm, length – 32 cm, width – 12 cm</size><investigation caption="Researches">Aspelin found in 1888 according to message from Safyanov. It was copied by Heikel  &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a name='source_121' class='myref' href='#label_121'&gt;121&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; (I, XIV) in 1889. The subsequent editions are based on that copy. The text is studied by S.E.Malov  &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a name='source_513' class='myref' href='#label_513'&gt;513&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, H.N.Orkun  &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a name='source_512' class='myref' href='#label_512'&gt;512&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, I.A.Batmanov  &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a name='source_511' class='myref' href='#label_511'&gt;511&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, etc.&#13;
</investigation><details caption="Additional information"></details><pdfs caption="Full-text information"><pdf f_author="Васильев Д.Д" f_title="Памятники тюркской рунической письменности азиатского ареала." f_in="Советская тюркология, 1976. – № 1. – С.71-81." f_name="Vasilev_1976.pdf"/></pdfs><refs><ref nm="121">Inscriptions de L'Orkhon recueillies par L’ Expedition Finnoise 1890 et puhliees par la Societe Finno-Ougrienne. Helsingfors. 1892.</ref><ref nm="513">Orkun H.N. Eski Turk Yazitlari, Istanbul, 1936, T-III. ss. 199-120.</ref><ref nm="512">Батманов И.А. Язык Енисейских памятников древнетюркской письменности. Фрунзе. 1959. С.160.</ref><ref nm="511">Orkun H.N. Eski Türk yazîtlari. Istanbul, 1936. t-III. 199-200 s.</ref></refs></root>
