<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<root><title>Uyk Oorzaq II (е-109)</title><time></time><hronology caption="Historical definition"></hronology><history></history><names caption="Names">Уюк-Оорзак I-III, Е 109</names><place caption="Places">Found on sowing areas in Oorzak near the basin Uyk.</place><store>Stored in the Tyva Museum.</store><general caption="Specification">Барлығы 4+1 жол мәтін қашалған. 4 жол жалпақ бетіне, 1 жол жіңішке бетіне қашалған. Бітіктастың төменгі жағында петроглиф суреттер мен таңба қашалған. Тастың беті минерал қабыршақтарымен қапталған. 1 және 3 жолдардың арасында едәуір ашық. Жіңішке бетке қашалған 5 жол түгел дерлік өшіп қалған.</general><description>The flat stele is made of red sandstone. Split to two parts. There are 4 lines of text on wide face and 1 line on narrow side. There are ancient images and a sign below the wide face. The surface of the stone is significantly covered by mineral stratifications. There are extensive lacunas in the middle of the line 1 and 3, the 5th line (on the narrow side) is almost erased.</description><size caption="Size">Height – 190 cm, length – 41-43 cm, width – 15 cm, height – 95 cm, length – 60-40, width – 8 cm</size><investigation caption="Researches">The archeological expedition of Tyva Scientific and Research Institute of Language, Literature and History found in 1974 (ТНИИЯЛИ - Gryaznov, Mannay-uul). Investigated by Z.B.Chadamba  &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a name='source_494' class='myref' href='#label_494'&gt;494&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;,  &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a name='source_495' class='myref' href='#label_495'&gt;495&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;,  &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a name='source_496' class='myref' href='#label_496'&gt;496&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, D.D.Vasilev  &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a name='source_497' class='myref' href='#label_497'&gt;497&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.</investigation><details caption="Additional information"></details><pdfs caption="Full-text information"><pdf f_author="Васильев Д.Д" f_title="Памятники тюркской рунической письменности азиатского ареала." f_in="Советская тюркология, 1976. – № 1. – С.71-81." f_name="Vasilev_1976.pdf"/></pdfs><refs><ref nm="494">Кызласов И. Л. Средневековая эпитафия из Малиновки (Тува). - СТ, 1977, N 2, с. 74-78.</ref><ref nm="495">Чадамба 3.Б. Древнетюркские надписи из урочища Оорзак. - УЗ ТНИИЯЛИ, вып. 17. Кызыл, 1975, c. 254-259</ref><ref nm="496">Чадамба 3.Б. О древнетюркской рунической надписи Оорзак I из Тувы. - В кн.: Этнические и культурные связи тюркских народов СССР. Тезисы докладов и сообщений (Всесоюзной тюркологической конференции). Алма-Ата, 1976, с. 107-108</ref><ref nm="497">Чадамба 3.Б., Васильев Д.Д. Тюркские рунические надписи Уюк-Оорзак. - В кн.: Новейшие исследования по археологии Тувы и этногенезу тувинцев. Кызыл, 1980, с. 131-143.</ref></refs></root>
