<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<root><title>Chaa-Hol IX (e-21)</title><time></time><hronology caption="Historical definition"></hronology><history></history><names caption="Names">Чаа-Холь IX, Е 21, Стела Кызыльского собрания</names><place caption="Places">Monuments of this group were found in a valley near the river Chaa-Hol, the left inflow of Ulug-Hem, in 25 km above the mouth of river Hemchik. This district is on the bottom of water basin Sayano-Shushenskii now. All monuments of the group, except Е 15, are in museum exhibitions.&#13;
</place><store>Researchers of Sayan-Tuva expedition moved the stone to the Tyva museum in Kyzyl in 1973. Inv #28.</store><general caption="Specification">The stele is made of gray-green slate with irregular form. The surface is roughly squared, sides are smoothed.&#13;
The stone is split into parts. Considerably destroyed, therefore its visual attribute is appeared inconvenient. There was preliminary publication in 1978 under the conditional name "Stela Kyzylskogo sobraniya".&#13;
</general><description>The epitaph text in 3 lines is located vertically and spirally twists the stone. Lines I and II are visible now. The line III was considered in former publications. There is a tamga in bottom.&#13;
</description><size caption="Size">Height – 236 cm, length – 38 cm, width – 17 cm</size><investigation caption="Researches">Aspelin found in 1888 according to message from Safyanov. Heikel made a photo of it in 1889. The subsequent editions are based on that copy. The text is studied by S.E.Malov &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a name='source_513' class='myref' href='#label_513'&gt;513&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, H.N.Orkun  &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a name='source_512' class='myref' href='#label_512'&gt;512&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, I.A.Batmanov  &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a name='source_511' class='myref' href='#label_511'&gt;511&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, etc. </investigation><details caption="Additional information"></details><pdfs caption="Full-text information"><pdf f_author="Васильев Д.Д" f_title="Памятники тюркской рунической письменности азиатского ареала." f_in="Советская тюркология, 1976. – № 1. – С.71-81." f_name="Vasilev_1976.pdf"/></pdfs><refs><ref nm="513">Orkun H.N. Eski Turk Yazitlari, Istanbul, 1936, T-III. ss. 199-120.</ref><ref nm="512">Батманов И.А. Язык Енисейских памятников древнетюркской письменности. Фрунзе. 1959. С.160.</ref><ref nm="511">Orkun H.N. Eski Türk yazîtlari. Istanbul, 1936. t-III. 199-200 s.</ref></refs></root>
