<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<root><title>Ochury Аchury (e-26)</title><time></time><hronology caption="Historical definition"></hronology><history></history><names caption="Names">Очуры, Ачуры, Е 26</names><place caption="Places">The stele was found in 20 km from village Ochury in the central part of steppe Koybalskoy between channels of the rivers Yenisei and Abakan.</place><store>Local authorities of Shushensk moved to the Minusinsk museum. Inv.# 32.</store><general caption="Specification">The stela is made of brown sandstone. Square in section. Surfaces are processed.</general><description>The epitaph text in 13 lines is located vertically on all four sides. On three sides for four lines on each are in half-cartouche frame. Some signs of one line are hardly noticed on the fourth side. The inscription is considerably destroyed. Reconstruction is made by Vasiliyev on basis of the copy of  Radloff's Atlas  &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a name='source_122' class='myref' href='#label_122'&gt;122&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; with some specifications after its visual verification with the original. &#13;
The composition of lines represents boustrophedon. &#13;
</description><size caption="Size">Height – 205 cm, length – 30 cm, width – 30 cm</size><investigation caption="Researches">Kostrov found in 1857. Fallenberg made a copy of the inscription (the copy is transferred to Radloff) in 1859. He had taken out the stele by order of Kostrov to Shushenskii. Then the local authorities had delivered to the Minusinsk museum.</investigation><details caption="Additional information"></details><pdfs caption="Full-text information"><pdf f_author="Васильев Д.Д" f_title="Памятники тюркской рунической письменности азиатского ареала." f_in="Советская тюркология, 1976. – № 1. – С.71-81." f_name="Vasilev_1976.pdf"/></pdfs><refs><ref nm="122">Radloff W. Atlas der Alterthümer der Mongolei. Arbeiten der Orchon Expedition. I-IV. St.Petersburg, 1892, 1893, 1896, 1899. ; Радлов В.В.Атлас древностей Монголии. Труды Орхонской экспедиции, I-IV. СПб., 1892, 1893, 1896, 1899.</ref></refs></root>
