<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<root><title>Ottuq Dash I (е-4)</title><time>VIII-IX ғ</time><hronology caption="Historical definition"></hronology><history></history><names caption="Names">Е 4, Оттук-Даш I, Тувинская стела B</names><place caption="Places">Three steles, gray sandstones found near the mountain Ottuq-Dash, the left coast of river Ulug-Kem, in 30 km below the mouth of river Elegest.</place><store>Adriyanov delivered to the Minusinsk museum on a raft across Yenisei in 1915.</store><general caption="Specification">1 жол мәтін кеңінен атыздалып қашалған. Тастың бір бетіне ұзына бойы жазылған.</general><description>The stele almost square in section, the surface is roughly polished, sides are precisely angled.&#13;
The inscription is cut by relief wide grooves in one line on all length of the stele. The bottom, apparently, is broken off.</description><size caption="Size">Height – 85 cm, length – 18 cm</size><investigation caption="Researches">Aspelin found in 1888 following the report of Martyanov. D.Klements made a special route of Orhon expedition, searched for the stele, but couldn't find it. The copy of the stele was made by Oshurkov in 1892 and delivered to Radloff. Investigated by W.Radloff  &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a name='source_122' class='myref' href='#label_122'&gt;122&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; (LXXXV, figs. 1), S.V.Kiselev  &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a name='source_498' class='myref' href='#label_498'&gt;498&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, S.E.Malov  &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a name='source_501' class='myref' href='#label_501'&gt;501&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, H.N.Orkhun  &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a name='source_500' class='myref' href='#label_500'&gt;500&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, etc.</investigation><details caption="Additional information"></details><pdfs caption="Full-text information"><pdf f_author="Васильев Д.Д" f_title="Памятники тюркской рунической письменности азиатского ареала." f_in="Советская тюркология, 1976. – № 1. – С.71-81." f_name="Vasilev_1976.pdf"/></pdfs><refs><ref nm="122">Radloff W. Atlas der Alterthümer der Mongolei. Arbeiten der Orchon Expedition. I-IV. St.Petersburg, 1892, 1893, 1896, 1899. ; Радлов В.В.Атлас древностей Монголии. Труды Орхонской экспедиции, I-IV. СПб., 1892, 1893, 1896, 1899.</ref><ref nm="498">Васильев Д.Д., Чадамба 3.Б. Древнетюркские эпиграфические памятники из долины р. Уюк. - ТСб-1977. М., 1981, с. 63-75.</ref><ref nm="501">Orkun H.N. Eski Türk yazîtlari. Istanbul, 1936. T-III. 49 s.</ref><ref nm="500">Батманов И.А. Язык Енисейских памятников древнетюркской письменности. Фрунзе. 1959. С. 144.</ref></refs></root>
